<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <Fruits>
    <Food>
        <name>Apples</name>
        <image>apples</image>
        <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 19 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 12-1/4 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 48 pounds and yields 16 to 19 quarts-an average of 2-3/4 pounds per quart.
            Quality: Select apples that are juicy, crispy, and preferably both sweet and tart.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners and Using Boiling Water Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash, peel, and core apples. To prevent discoloration, slice apples into water containing ascorbic acid. Raw packs make poor quality products. Place drained slices in large saucepan and add 1 pint water or very light, light, or medium syrup per 5 pounds of sliced apples. Boil 5 minutes, stirring occasionally to prevent burning. Fill jars with hot slices and hot syrup or water, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Adjust lids and process.

                Processing directions for canning sliced apples in a boiling-water, a dial, or a weighted-gauge canner are given in Table 1, Table 2, and Table 3. Tables at URl</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Syrup Pack is preferred for apples to be used for uncooked desserts or fruit cocktail. A sugar or dry pack is good for pie making.

                Select full-flavored apples that are crisp and firm, not mealy in texture. Wash, peel and core. Slice medium apples into twelfths, large ones into sixteenths.

                Syrup Pack – Use cold 40 percent syrup. To prevent browning, add 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart of syrup.

                Slice apples directly into syrup in container starting with 1/2 cup syrup to a pint container. Press fruit down in containers and add enough syrup to cover. Leave headspace. Place a small piece of crumpled water-resistant paper on top to hold fruit down. Seal and freeze.

                Sugar Pack – To prevent darkening, dissolve 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid in 3 tablespoons water. Sprinkle over the fruit. Or, apple slices can be steam blanched for 11/2 to 2 minutes.

                Mix 1/2 cup sugar with 1 quart (1 1/4 pounds) of fruit. Pack apples into containers and press fruit down, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Dry Pack – Follow the directions for Sugar Pack, omitting the sugar. Treated apple slices can also be frozen first on a tray and then packed into containers as soon as they are frozen. For more information, see other unsweetened packs.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/homemade-oven-baked-apple-chips/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/apple_sliced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apple.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/homemade-oven-baked-apple-chips/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
    <Food>
        <name>Apricots</name>
        <image>apricots</image>
        <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 16 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 10 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 50 pounds and yields 20 to 25 quarts-an average of 2¼ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select firm, well-colored mature fruit of ideal quality for eating fresh.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners and Using Boiling Water Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash fruit well if skins are not removed. (Optional procedure for removal of skins - Dip washed fruit in boiling water for 30 to 60 seconds until skins loosen. Dip quickly in cold water and slip off skins.) Cut prepared apricots in half, remove pits and slice if desired. To prevent darkening, keep peeled fruit in ascorbic acid solution. Prepare and boil a very light, light, or medium syrup or pack apricots in water, apple juice, or white grape juice.

                Raw packs make poor quality apricots.

                Hot pack – In a large saucepan place drained fruit in syrup, water, or juice and bring to boil. Fill jars with hot fruit and cooking liquid, leaving ½-inch headspace. Place halves in layers, cut side down.

                Raw pack – Fill jars with raw fruit, cut side down, and add hot water, juice, or syrup, leaving ½-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process.

                Processing directions for canning apricots in a boiling-water canner are given in Table 1.

                Processing directions for canning apricots in a dial or weighted-gauge canner are given in Table 2 and Table 3.Tables info in URL.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, ripe, uniformly yellow apricots. Sort, wash, halve and pit. Peel and slice if desired. If apricots are not peeled, heat them in boiling water 1/2 minute to keep skins from toughening during freezing. Cool in cold water and drain.

                Syrup Pack – Use cold 40 percent syrup. For a better quality frozen product, add 3/4 teaspoon (2250 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart of syrup. Pack apricots directly into containers. Cover with syrup, leaving headspace. Place a small piece of crumpled water-resistant paper on top to hold fruit down. Seal and freeze.

                Sugar Pack – Before combining apricots with sugar, give the fruit the following treatment to prevent darkening:

                Dissolve 1/4 teaspoon (750 mg) ascorbic acid in 3 tablespoons cold water and sprinkle over 1 quart (7/8 pound) of fruit. Mix 1/2 cup sugar with each quart of fruit. Stir until sugar is dissolved. Pack apricots into containers and press down until fruit is covered with juice, leaving headspace. Place a small piece of crumpled water-resistant paper on top to hold fruit down. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
        <dryingMethod>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Apricots#:~:text=Line%20a%20baking%20sheet%20with,to%20dry%20apricots%2C%20read%20on!</dryingMethod>
        <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/apricot_sliced.html</canningUrl>
        <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apricot.html</freezingUrl>
        <dryingUrl>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Apricots#:~:text=Line%20a%20baking%20sheet%20with,to%20dry%20apricots%2C%20read%20on!</dryingUrl>
        <type>fruit</type>
    </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Avocados</name>
            <image>avocados</image>
            <canningMethod>Here’s a quick and easy pickling solution. Multiply by the number of avocados you have.

                Ingredients

                1 ripe but firm avocado
                4 tablespoons vinegar
                2 tablespoons water (optional)
                1 to 2 teaspoons sugar (or to taste)
                1/2 teaspoon salt (or to taste)
                (see variations below)

                Directions

                Choose firm but ripe avocados. Peel, pit, and slice or cube the avocado flesh.
                In a bowl large enough to hold the avocado pieces, stir together vinegar, water, sugar, and salt until sugar and salt are completely dissolved.
                Pour vinegar mixture over slices or cubes of avocado.
                Cover, refrigerate, and use within 3 days.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select avocados that yield to gentle pressure with rinds free from dark blemishes. Peel fruit, cut in half and remove pit.

                Avocados are best frozen as purée – unsweetened for salads and sandwiches, sweetened for other uses. Avocados are not satisfactorily frozen whole or sliced. For a better quality product, add 1/4 teaspoon (750 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart of purée or add 1 tablespoon lemon juice for each 2 avocados.

                Pack into container, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.dryingallfoods.com/dehydrating-avocado/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/2724-avocado-preserving-methods/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/avocado.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.dryingallfoods.com/dehydrating-avocado/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Bananas</name>
            <image>banana</image>
            <canningMethod>Bananas can be used as an ingredient in home canning, but they can’t be canned plain on their own.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm ripe bananas. Peel; mash thoroughly. Add 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid per cup of mashed banana. Package in moisture-vapor resistant container. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://naturallyella.com/baked-banana-chips/#:~:text=Slice%20bananas%20into%201%2F16,out%2C%202%2D3%20hours.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.healthycanning.com/canning-bananas/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/banana.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://naturallyella.com/baked-banana-chips/#:~:text=Slice%20bananas%20into%201%2F16,out%2C%202%2D3%20hours.</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Berries</name>
            <image>berries</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select full-flavored, ripe berries. Remove leaves, stems and immature or defective berries.

                Dry Pack – Do not wash berries. Washing results in a tougher skinned product. Pack berries into containers, leaving headspace. Berries can also be frozen first on a tray and then packed into containers as soon as they are frozen. Seal and freeze. Wash before using.

                Crushed or Puréed – Wash the berries. Crush, press berries through a fine sieve, or purée in a blender or food processor. Mix 1 to 1 1/8 cups of sugar with each quart (2 pounds) of crushed berries or purée. Stir until sugar is dissolved. Pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://jomygosh.com/2015/01/easiest-way-to-dry-blueberries-ever/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/blueberry.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://jomygosh.com/2015/01/easiest-way-to-dry-blueberries-ever/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Cherries</name>
            <image>cherries</image>
            <canningMethod>Sweet or Sour Cherries - Whole
                Quantity: An average of 17½ pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 11 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A lug weighs 25 pounds and yields 8 to 12 quarts – an average of 2½ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select bright, uniformly colored cherries that are mature (of ideal quality for eating fresh or cooking).

                Please read Using Pressure Canners and Using Boiling Water Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Stem and wash cherries. Remove pits if desired. If pitted, place cherries in water containing ascorbic acid to prevent stem-end discoloration. If canned unpitted, prick skins on opposite sides with a clean needle to prevent splitting. Cherries may be canned in water, apple juice, white-grape juice, or syrup. If syrup is desired, select and prepare preferred type as directed.Hot pack – In a large saucepan add ½ cup water, juice, or syrup for each quart of drained fruit and bring to boil. Fill jars with cherries and cooking liquid, leaving ½-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Add ½ cup hot water, juice, or syrup to each jar. Fill jars with drained cherries, shaking down gently as you fill. Add more hot liquid, leaving ½-inch headspace. Adjust lids and process.

                Processing directions for canning cherries in a boiling-water, a dial, or a weighted-gauge canner are given in Table 1, Table 2, and Table 3. Tables at URL</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select bright, fully ripened cherries of dark colored varieties. Wash, stem and pit.

                Syrup Pack – Use cold, 40 percent syrup. For a better quality product add 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart syrup. Pack fruit and cover with syrup, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-cherries-dehydrator-method-1327532</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/cherry_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/cherry_sweet.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-cherries-dehydrator-method-1327532</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Chokecherries</name>
            <image>chokecherries</image>
            <canningMethod>ChokeCherry Jelly

                Ingredients
                4 cups chokecherry juice
                1/4 cup of lemon juice
                1 1/2– 2 cups sugar OR 1 1/2 cups honey
                4 t. Pomona’s Pectin (like this)
                4 t. calcium water (included in Pomona’s pectin)

                Instructions
                Step 1: *How to Make Chokecherry Juice* If you have a juicer, use it! I don’t, so I use this method:
                Clean, wash, and remove stems from berries
                Place in a large pot filled with enough water to just cover the fruit
                Simmer 15-30 minutes until fruit softens
                Use a potato masher to mash the juice out
                Strain through a cheesecloth-lined colander or jelly strainer
                Save the juice and discard pulp/pits
                Step 2: Mix chokecherry juice, lemon juice, and 4 teaspoons calcium water in a pot
                Thoroughly mix sugar or honey in separate bowl with 4 teaspoons pectin &amp; set aside
                Step 3: Bring juice mixture to a boil
                Add pectin/sugar mixture, mix until completely incorporated, then return to a boil
                Remove from heat, get ready to place it in your sterilized canning jars
                Step 4: Fill the jars, leaving 1/4″ headspace
                Boil in a hot-water bath canner 10 minutes (add an extra minute for every 1,000 feet you are above sea level)</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select bright red, tree ripened cherries. Wash, stem and pit.

                Syrup Pack – Pack cherries into containers and cover with cold 50 per cent syrup. Leave headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Sugar Pack – To 1 quart (1 and 1/3 pounds) cherries add 3/4 cup sugar. Mix until sugar is dissolved. Pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://openprairie.sdstate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1485&amp;context=extension_extra#:~:text=Lay%20the%20patties%20on%20a,hot%2C%20soapy%20water%20and%20dried.&amp;text=Leave%20about%201%2F2%20inch,occur%20throughout%20the%20drying%20process.&amp;text=Chokecherry%20patties%20will%20take%2012%2D16%20hours%20to%20dry.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.theprairiehomestead.com/2012/08/how-to-make-chokecherry-jelly-low-sugar-and-honey-variations.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/cherry_sour.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://openprairie.sdstate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1485&amp;context=extension_extra#:~:text=Lay%20the%20patties%20on%20a,hot%2C%20soapy%20water%20and%20dried.&amp;text=Leave%20about%201%2F2%20inch,occur%20throughout%20the%20drying%20process.&amp;text=Chokecherry%20patties%20will%20take%2012%2D16%20hours%20to%20dry.</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Citrus Fruits</name> <!--lemon curd-->
            <image>citrus_fruits</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/lemon_curd.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/freezer_lemoncurd.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.trail.recipes/dehydrating123/dehydrating123-why-and-how-to-dehydrate-citrus-fruits/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/lemon_curd.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/freezer_lemoncurd.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.trail.recipes/dehydrating123/dehydrating123-why-and-how-to-dehydrate-citrus-fruits/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Crabapple</name>
            <image>crabapple</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/crab_apple_spiced.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apple.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://homecookedvegan.blogspot.com/2016/01/dehydrated-crab-apples.html</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/crab_apple_spiced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apple.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://homecookedvegan.blogspot.com/2016/01/dehydrated-crab-apples.html</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Currants Figs</name>
            <image>currants_figs</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/fig.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/fig.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Figs#:~:text=To%20dry%20figs%2C%20start%20by,for%20up%20to%2036%20hours.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/fig.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/fig.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Figs#:~:text=To%20dry%20figs%2C%20start%20by,for%20up%20to%2036%20hours.</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Grapes</name>
            <image>grapes</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/grapes_whole.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/grape.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.seriouseats.com/recipes/2017/02/oven-dried-grapes-raisins-recipe.html</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/grapes_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/grape.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.seriouseats.com/recipes/2017/02/oven-dried-grapes-raisins-recipe.html</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Melons</name>
            <image>melons</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/green_mangoes.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/melon.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/888-how-to-dry-melon-slices/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/green_mangoes.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/melon.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/888-how-to-dry-melon-slices/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Mint/Herbs</name>
            <image>mint</image>
            <canningMethod>https://canningdiva.com/canning-mint-jelly/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/herbs.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruce.com/how-to-dry-and-store-herbs-1403397</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://canningdiva.com/canning-mint-jelly/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/herbs.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruce.com/how-to-dry-and-store-herbs-1403397</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peaches</name>
            <image>peaches</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/peach_sliced.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/peach.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dry-peaches-in-a-dehydrator-1327526</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/peach_sliced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/peach.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dry-peaches-in-a-dehydrator-1327526</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Pears</name>
            <image>pears</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pear_halved.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-pears-in-dehydrator-1327580</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pear_halved.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-pears-in-dehydrator-1327580</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Pineapple</name>
            <image>pineapple</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pineapple.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pineapple.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://selfproclaimedfoodie.com/oven-dried-pineapple/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pineapple.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pineapple.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://selfproclaimedfoodie.com/oven-dried-pineapple/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Plums</name>
            <image>plums</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/plum_halved.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/plum.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://frugalfamilyhome.com/food/drying-foods/how-to-dry-plums</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/plum_halved.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/plum.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://frugalfamilyhome.com/food/drying-foods/how-to-dry-plums</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Quince</name>
            <image>quince</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/asian_pears.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Preserving-Apples-Pears-and-Quince.pdf</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/asian_pears.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Preserving-Apples-Pears-and-Quince.pdf</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
<!--        <Food>-->
<!--            <name>Rhubarb</name>-->
<!--            <image>rhubarb</image>-->
<!--            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/rhubarb_stewed.html</canningMethod>-->
<!--            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/rhubarb.html</freezingMethod>-->
<!--            <dryingMethod>https://madaboutmacarons.com/dried-rhubarb-chips/</dryingMethod>-->
<!--            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/rhubarb_stewed.html</canningUrl>-->
<!--            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/rhubarb.html</freezingUrl>-->
<!--            <dryingUrl>https://madaboutmacarons.com/dried-rhubarb-chips/</dryingUrl>-->
<!--            <type>fruit</type>-->
<!--        </Food>-->
        <Food>
            <name>Strawberries</name>
            <image>strawberries</image>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/strawberry.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/oven-dried-strawberries/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/strawberry.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/oven-dried-strawberries/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
    </Fruits>

</resources>