<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <Tutorials>
        <String>https://nchfp.uga.edu/publications/uga/using_press_canners.html</String>
        <String>https://nchfp.uga.edu/publications/usda/GUIDE01_HomeCan_rev0715.pdf</String>
    </Tutorials>

    <Vegetables>
        <Food>
            <name>Artichokes</name>
            <canningMethod>This kitchen project delivers both flavor and texture unlike any store-bought artichokes. Home-canned, marinated artichoke hearts liven up pizza, a salad or a sandwich.

                Beware: The tannins in raw artichoke will stain your hands. Lemon juice will remove the stain.

                You'll need 3 sanitized pint jars with new lids and rings; see the NOTE, below.

                Make Ahead: The artichokes need 1 month to cure, during which time their texture changes from firm to velvety while their structure is retained. If you choose to skip the water-bath canning called for here, refrigerate the sealed jars of artichokes for 1 month before serving. (Artichokes that are not water-bath-canned will not achieve the same silky texture as those that are.) The water-bath-canned jars of artichokes need to cool for 12 hours. They are shelf stable for 1 year. Once opened, the jars should be refrigerated and used within a month.SERVINGS: 9 - 15

                Yield: (makes 3 pints)

                INGREDIENTS
                4 lemons
                9 medium or 15 baby artichokes
                1/4 cup plus 3 teaspoons kosher salt or sea salt
                1 cup distilled white vinegar, plus more as needed
                1/4 cup white wine vinegar
                1/4 cup mild olive oil, or more as needed
                1 tablespoon dried oregano
                3/4 teaspoon crushed red pepper flakes
                3 cloves garlic, root ends trimmed
                Three 1-inch strips lemon zest

                DIRECTIONS
                Halve and juice the lemons. Place the spent lemon halves in a 5-quart nonreactive (not aluminum or copper) pot; fill it with cold water. Strain and reserve the juice for the marinade.

                To trim the artichokes, pull the leaves from each one, snapping them where they naturally break. Use a sharp knife or vegetable peeler to peel the choke, then make a clean cut across the end of the stem, retaining the tender portion. Use a grapefruit spoon, melon baller or side of a teaspoon to scrape away the fuzzy choke, revealing the meaty part of it, then quarter the entire choke. (For baby artichokes, trim only to any inner leaves without a thorn.) As each choke is trimmed, drop it into the pot.

                Add 1/4 cup of salt. Bring the pot filled with lemon water and artichokes to a boil over high heat, then reduce the heat to medium or medium-low so the water is barely bubbling. Cook, uncovered, until fork-tender, about 10 minutes.

                Meanwhile, make the marinade: Combine the reserved lemon juice, vinegars, oil, oregano, crushed red pepper flakes and garlic cloves in a small saucepan over high heat. Bring to a boil; cook for 5 minutes, then remove from the heat.

                Use a slotted spoon to transfer the artichokes to the sanitized jars, dividing evenly and stacking the small ones and first cutting the medium ones into quarters. Tuck them in as tightly as possible without breaking or bruising.

                Whisk the marinade well and divide among the jars. If there is not enough marinade to cover, add oil as needed to leave 1/2 inch headspace at the top of each jar. Make sure 1 garlic clove, 1 strip of lemon zest and 1 teaspoon salt goes into each jar.

                Run a chopstick or flat plastic knife along the inside of the jar to remove any air bubbles. Clean the rim of each jar with distilled white vinegar to cut residual oils, place the warmed lids on and finger-tighten the rings (not too tight). Process in the boiling water bath for 15 minutes (see NOTE, below). Turn off the heat and let the jars rest in the pot for 10 minutes. Use tongs to transfer the jars to a clean, folded dish towel to cool over several hours.

                Store the water-bath-canned jars in a cool space to cure for 1 month.

                NOTE: Water-bath canning safely seals high acid, low pH foods in jars. The time for processing in the water-bath is calculated based on the size of the jar and the consistency and density of the food. For safety's sake, do not alter the jar size, ingredients, ratios or processing time in any canning recipes. If moved to change any of these items, simply put the prepared food in the refrigerator and eat within a week.

                Fill a large canning kettle or deep stockpot two-thirds full with water. To keep the jars from rattling against the pot, place a rack in the pot (a cake rack works well, or a folded dish towel is equally effective). Sanitize the jars in a short dishwasher cycle or by boiling them in a canning kettle or pot for 10 minutes. Fill a small saucepan with water and add the rings. Bring to a boil over high heat, slip in the lids and turn off the heat.

                Use a jar lifter or tongs to lower the filled, sealed jars upright into the boiling water-bath. When all the jars are in place, the water should be 1 to 2 inches above the top of the jar. Add water as needed. Bring the water to a low boil before starting the timer for processing.

                At the end of processing, turn off the heat and let the jars sit in the water bath until the boiling has stopped. This will reduce siphoning -- when the food burbles up under the lid, breaking the seal. Use the jar lifter or tongs to transfer the jars to a folded towel, placed upright. Leave the jars until they have completely cooled, at least 12 hours. Remove the rings and test the seal by lifting the jar by the lid. The lid should hold fast. Label and store in a cool, dry, dark space.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select those with uniformly green color, compact globes and tightly adhering leaves. Remove all leaves and choke or fuzzy portion. The portion that is left at the base is the heart. Cut away the stem just below the heart and trim any woody portions. Wash hearts in cold water and drain.

                Water blanch 7 minutes. Cook, drain and pack, leaving no head space. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.homestratosphere.com/how-to-store-artichokes/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.washingtonpost.com/recipes/home-canned-artichoke-hearts/14027/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/artichoke.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.homestratosphere.com/how-to-store-artichokes/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Asparagus</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 24½ pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 16 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A crate weighs 31 pounds and yields 7 to 12 quarts--an average of 3½ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Use tender, tight-tipped spears, 4 to 6 inches long.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash asparagus and trim off tough scales. Break off tough stems and wash again. Cut into 1-inch pieces or can whole.

                Hot pack – Cover asparagus with boiling water. Boil 2 or 3 minutes. Loosely fill jars with hot asparagus, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Fill jars with raw asparagus, packing as tightly as possible without crushing, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Add 1 teaspoon of salt per quart to the jars, if desired. Add boiling water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process as recommended in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the method of canning used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young tender spears. Wash thoroughly and sort into sizes. Trim stalks by removing scales with a sharp knife. Cut into even lengths to fit containers.

                Water blanch small spears 2 minutes, medium spears 3 minutes and large spears 4 minutes.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://preparednessmama.com/dehydrating-asparagus/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/asparagus_spears.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/asparagus.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://preparednessmama.com/dehydrating-asparagus/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Beans: Green, Snap, or Wax</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 14 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 9 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 30 pounds and yields 12 to 20 quarts – an average of 2 pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select filled but tender, crisp pods. Remove and discard diseased and rusty pods.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash beans and trim ends. Leave whole or cut or snap into 1-inch pieces.

                Hot pack –Cover with boiling water; boil 5 minutes. Fill jars loosely with beans, leaving 1-inch headspace. Add 1 teaspoon of canning salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Cover beans with hot cooking liquid, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Fill jars tightly with raw beans, leaving 1-inch headspace. Add 1 teaspoon of canning salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Add boiling water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process in a pressure canner following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the type of canner being used. (There is no safe option for processing green beans in a boiling water canner.)</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young tender pods when the seed is first formed. Wash in cold water, snip and cut into 2 to 4-inch lengths.

                Water blanch 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-store-dried-beans-1389336#:~:text=Storing%20the%20Beans&amp;text=Transfer%20your%20dried%20beans%20to,dry%20place%20away%20from%20sunlight.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/beans_snap_italian.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/bean_green.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-store-dried-beans-1389336#:~:text=Storing%20the%20Beans&amp;text=Transfer%20your%20dried%20beans%20to,dry%20place%20away%20from%20sunlight.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Beans: Lima, Butter, or Pinto</name>
            <canningMethod>Beans or Peas - Shelled, Dried: All Varieties

                Quantity: An average of 5 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 3¼ pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints--an average of ¾ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select mature, dry seeds. Sort out and discard discolored seeds.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Place dried beans or peas in a large pot and cover with water. Soak 12 to 18 hours in a cool place. Drain water. To quickly hydrate beans, you may cover sorted and washed beans with boiling water in a saucepan. Boil 2 minutes, remove from heat, soak 1 hour and drain. Cover beans soaked by either method with fresh water and boil 30 minutes. Add ½ teaspoon of salt per pint or 1 teaspoon per quart to the jar, if desired. Fill jars with beans or peas and cooking water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process as recommended in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the method of canning used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Harvest while the seed is in the green stage. Wash, shell and sort according to size.

                Water blanch small beans 2 minutes, medium beans 3 minutes and large beans 4 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.
            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>Traditional Method of Drying Beans &amp; Peas
                The traditional method was to leave the beans in pods on the plant for as long as possible. Once the weather changed the vines were uprooted and hung under cover, a greenhouse being most often used. When the pods were brittle, the beans were shelled and stored.

                Being reliant on the weather, the traditional method of drying beans was pretty hit and miss. Improperly dried beans would often develop mould and not be fit to eat. The same problem often hit saved seed.

                Oven Drying Beans
                You can dry beans and peas in an oven if you don’t have a dehydrator. The best type of oven is an electric fan oven but a standard or a gas oven will do the job. Please note that beans dried in this manner are not suitable for sprouting as the blanching kills the germ.

                Pod your peas or beans and drop into cold water. The reason for this is you may well have a few pea maggots and they will float out in the water.
                Now blanch for about three minutes. Since they inevitably slip through the holes in a blanching basket, we just drop them straight into the blanching water and then use a fine sieve to fish them out.
                Don’t cool after blanching, just dry them on a towel before spreading onto trays and drying in the oven. The ideal is to dry at a temperature starting at 50°C/120°F/Gas Mark 0 and then increase the temperature slowly up to 65°C/150°F/Gas Mark 0.
                The beans and peas are dry when they are quite crisp. Depending on their size, this takes between 2-3 hours. Pack in tightly corked bottles or airtight containers and store in a dry, dark place.

                The only real drawback with dried beans is that they require soaking prior to use. If you’re the sort of person who plans ahead with your meals, then it’s no problem but if you are the type of person who gets home and then decides what to eat, dried beans can be difficult.
                Usually you should soak dried beans and peas in cold water for about 12 hours to fully re-hydrate them before use. If you’re in a hurry, simply put your beans or peas into a large saucepan with plenty of cold water. Bring to the boil and boil vigorously for two or three minutes. Remove from the heat, cover the pan and leave for three quarters to an hour by which time they should be re-hydrated.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/beans_peas_shelled.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/bean_lima.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.allotment-garden.org/recipe/drying-dehydrating/drying-beans-peas/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Beets</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 21 pounds (without tops) is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 13-1/2 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel (without tops) weighs 52 pounds and yields 15 to 20 quarts--an average of 3 pounds per quart.

                Quality: Beets with a diameter of 1 to 2 inches are preferred for whole packs. Beets larger than 3 inches in diameter are often fibrous.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Trim off beet tops, leaving an inch of stem and roots to reduce bleeding of color. Scrub well. Cover with boiling water. Boil until skins slip off easily; about 15 to 25 minutes depending on size. Cool just enough to handle without burning yourself, then remove skins, and trim off stems and roots. The beets should remain warm or hot going into the jars. Leave baby beets whole. Cut medium or large beets into 1/2-inch cubes or slices. Halve or quarter very large slices. Add 1 teaspoon of salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Fill jars with hot beets and fresh hot water that has been brought to a boil first (not the water you used to boil the beets with), leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the method of canning used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select deep, uniformly-red, tender, young beets. Wash and sort according to size. Trim tops, leaving 1/2 inch of stems and tap root, to prevent bleeding of color during cooking.

                Cook in boiling water until tender-for small beets 25 to 30 minutes; for medium beets 45 to 50 minutes.

                Cool promptly in cold water. Peel, remove stem and tap root, and cut into slices or cubes. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>Dried beets usually are reconstituted or added to soups and stews. If properly dried, beets retain their flavor and much of their nutritional value.

                Blanch the beets in boiling water for 20 minutes and transfer them into a container of ice water. Scrape the peels from the beets.

                Trim off the stems and taproot and slice the beets into uniform, 1/8-inch-wide strips. Chop the beets into 1/4-inch-thick pieces or grate them using a box grater.

                Heat the food dehydrator to 120 degrees Fahrenheit and lay the beet pieces about 1/4 inch apaprt from each other on the drying trays.

                If using an oven, heat it to the Warm setting. Place the beets on cooling racks covered with a piece of cheesecloth.

                Dry beet strips until they are brittle or crisp, about 8 hours, in the dehydrator; dry chopped or grated beets for four to six hours.

                If using the oven, dry beet strips for 4 hours and shredded beets for 2 hours.

                THINGS YOU WILL NEED
                Knife
                Box grater (optional)
                Food dehydrator
                Cooling or baking rack (optional)
                Cheesecloth (optional)
                TIP
                Pack the dried and cooled beets into dry, airtight containers or plastic bags that seal. Store the dried beets in a cool, dark place. Check the beets after a few days and then periodically to make sure they are completely dried. Use dried beets within six to 12 months. Discard the beets and disinfect the containers if you see signs of mold or other spoilage. Soak dried beets in cold water for one hour to reconstitute. Add dry or reconstituted beets to soups or stews. Dried beets will double in size when reconstituted.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/beets.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/beet.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://homesteady.com/13406978/how-to-dry-out-beets</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Broccoli</name>
            <canningMethod>Spicy Quick Pickled Broccoli

                Ingredients
                1 pound fresh broccoli
                sprinkling of sea salt
                3/4 cup unseasoned rice vinegar
                3 tablespoons sesame oil
                1 1/2 teaspoons chili paste
                1 teaspoon garlic, minced
                1 teaspoon granulated sugar
                Instructions
                Fill a large bowl with ice water and set aside.
                Cut the broccoli into uniform spears.  Rinse, drain, add them to a large bowl. Set aside.

                Place a steamer rack into a pot with the water level just below it.  Over high heat, bring the water to a boil and then add the broccoli to the rack, sprinkle it with salt and cover.  Turn the heat to low and steam just until the broccoli is tender, 4 to 5 minutes.

                Drain the broccoli and immediately add it to the bowl of ice water. Leave it for about 5 minutes, drain again, pat dry with a kitchen towel, and set aside. (The ice water "shocks" the broccoli, which stops the cooking process and helps keep the color bright.)

                In a medium-sized mixing bowl, whisk the vinegar with the sesame oil, chili paste, garlic, and sugar. Pour this mixture into a heavy-duty zip-lock bag and add the broccoli. Seal the bag, removing as much air as possible and place it in a bowl (in case it leaks), in the refrigerator.
                Let the broccoli marinate for about 1 hour, drain and serve.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, young, tender stalks with compact heads. Remove leaves and woody portions. Separate heads into convenient-size sections and immerse in brine (4 teaspoons salt to 1 gallon water) for 30 minutes to remove insects. Split lengthwise so flowerets are no more than 1 1/2 inches across.

                Water blanch 3 minutes in boiling water or steam blanch 5 minutes.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://joybileefarm.com/drying-broccoli-food-storage/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://cookingontheweekends.com/spicy-quick-pickled-broccoli/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/broccoli.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://joybileefarm.com/drying-broccoli-food-storage/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Brussel Sprouts</name>
            <canningMethod>Zesty Pickled Brussels Sprouts

                Ingredients:
                2 pounds Brussels sprouts, trimmed and cut in half
                5 1-pint canning jars with lids and rings
                5 cloves garlic, divided
                1 1/4 teaspoons red pepper flakes, divided
                5 cups water
                5 cups distilled white vinegar
                7 tablespoons pickling salt

                Directions:
                Soak Brussels sprouts in a large bowl filled with lightly salted water for about 15 minutes. Drain well.

                Sterilize the jars and lids in boiling water for at least 5 minutes.

                Divide the drained Brussels sprouts evenly between jars, filling the jars about 3/4-inch from the top.

                Place 1 garlic clove and 1/4 teaspoon red pepper flakes in each jar.

                Bring vinegar, water, and pickling salt to a boil in a large pot over medium-high heat until the salt is dissolved, about 5 minutes.

                Pour the vinegar mixture into the jars, filling the jars to within 1/4 inch of the top.

                Run a knife or a thin spatula around the insides of the jars after they have been filled to remove any air bubbles.

                Wipe the rims of the jars with a moist paper towel to remove any food residue. Top with lids, and screw on rings.

                Place a rack in the bottom of a large stockpot, and fill stockpot halfway with water.

                Bring to a boil over high heat, then carefully lower the jars into the pot using a holder. Leave a 2-inch space between the jars. Pour in more boiling water if necessary, until the water level is at least 1 inch above the tops of the jars. Bring the water to a full boil, cover the pot, and process for 10 minutes.

                Remove the jars from the stockpot and place onto a cloth-covered or wood surface, several inches apart, until cool.

                Once cool, press the top of each lid with a finger, ensuring that the seal is tight (lid does not move up or down at all). Store in a cool, dark area, and wait at least 3 weeks before opening.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select green, firm and compact heads. Examine heads carefully to make sure they are free from insects. Trim, removing coarse outer leaves. Wash thoroughly. Sort into small, medium and large sizes.

                Water blanch small heads 3 minutes, medium heads 4 minutes and large heads 5 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://apps.chhs.colostate.edu/preservesmart/produce/drying/brussels-sprouts/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.allrecipes.com/recipe/220205/zesty-pickled-brussels-sprouts/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/brussel_sprouts.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://apps.chhs.colostate.edu/preservesmart/produce/drying/brussels-sprouts/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Cabbage or Chinese Cabbage</name>
            <canningMethod>Sauerkraut
                Ingredients:

                5 lbs cabbage (5 lbs)
                3 tablespoons pickling salt

                Instructions:
                Take cabbage, discard outer leaves.

                Wash heads under running water, shake excess water off.

                With a large knife such as a French knife, quarter the cabbage heads.
                Cut out and discard the cores.

                Slice the quartered cabbage into slices about 2 mm (.07 inches) thick (the thickness of a US / Cdn quarter or a 10 p piece.)

                Put cabbage either into a very large bowl or directly into the container you are going to use to ferment it in - whatever you prefer to be working in.

                Sprinkle the salt over and mix in.

                Some sources say to let it stand a bit so the salt will start drawing at least a bit of liquid out. Some suggest 10 minutes; the All New Ball says cover it and let stand for an hour.

                Begin pounding / crushing the cabbage, and keep on crushing it until a good amount of liquid has been released from the leaves.

                Ideally, you are going to be aiming for enough released liquid to cover the cabbage once in the fermenting container, but you may rarely get it at this point -- don't worry.

                Add to fermenting container, if it's not already.

                If you are doubling, tripling or quadrupling the recipe, start the next batch of cabbage now, then add to container.

                Repeat until you have prepped all the cabbage you planned to.

                When you are finished crushing, if the cabbage is not already in the fermentation container, move it all there.

                Be sure to leave a gap of 10 to 12 cm (4 to 5 inches) between the cabbage in the container, and the top rim of the container as headspace.

                If you have more cabbage than that, you'll need another container.

                If the juice you were able to produce was not sufficient to cover the cabbage, then make a brine (see directions below) and use that to top up with. (To be clear: you are not aiming to fill the container to the top rim with liquid; you are after enough liquid to completely submerge all the cabbage by 2 to 5 cm / 1 to 2 inches.) FIRST, though, see Linda Ziedrich suggestion in Brine section: she suggests waiting 24 hours to see if it will produce enough juice on its own before adding the extra brine.

                Cover cabbage with some sort of weight (see Weights Options below) to keep it safely below the surface of the liquid.

                Cover container with a large towel.

                Let ferment for 3 to 4 weeks or until cabbage is translucent.

                During fermentation, you may or may not need to check the cabbage frequently. It depends on the weights you use (see Weights Options below).</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Frozen cabbage or Chinese cabbage are suitable for use only as a cooked vegetable.

                Select freshly picked, solid heads. Trim coarse outer leaves from head. Cut into medium to coarse shreds or thin wedges, or separate head into leaves. Water blanch 1½ minutes.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://thesurvivalmom.com/how-to-dehydrate-cabbage/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.healthycanning.com/home-canned-sauerkraut/#The_recipe</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/cabbage.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://thesurvivalmom.com/how-to-dehydrate-cabbage/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Carrots</name>
            <canningMethod>Sliced or Diced
                Quantity: An average of 17-1/2 pounds (without tops) is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 11 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel (without tops) weighs 50 pounds and yields 17 to 25 quarts – an average of 2-1/2 pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select small carrots, preferably 1 to 1-1/4 inches in diameter. Larger carrots are often too fibrous.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash, peel, and rewash carrots. Slice or dice.

                Hot pack – Cover with boiling water; bring to boil and simmer for 5 minutes. Fill jars, leaving 1-inch of headspace.

                Raw pack – Fill jars tightly with raw carrots, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Add 1 teaspoon of salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Add hot cooking liquid or water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the method of canning used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young, tender, coreless, medium length carrots. Remove tops, wash and peel. Leave small carrots whole. Cut others into thin slices, 1/4-inch cubes or lengthwise strips.

                Water blanch small whole carrots 5 minutes, diced or sliced 2 minutes and lengthwise strips 2 minutes.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.simplycanning.com/how-to-dry-vegetables.html</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/carrots_sliced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/carrot.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.simplycanning.com/how-to-dry-vegetables.html</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Cauliflower</name>
            <canningMethod>https://recipes.howstuffworks.com/pickled-cauliflower-recipe.htm</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Choose compact white heads. Trim off leaves and cut head into pieces about 1 inch across. If necessary to remove insects, soak for 30 minutes in solution of salt and water (4 teaspoons salt per gallon water). Drain.

                Water blanch for 3 minutes in water containing 4 teaspoons salt per gallon water.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.trail.recipes/blog/how-to-make-dehydrated-cauliflower-rice/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://recipes.howstuffworks.com/pickled-cauliflower-recipe.htm</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/cauliflower.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.trail.recipes/blog/how-to-make-dehydrated-cauliflower-rice/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Celery</name>
            <canningMethod>The USDA never backed canning plain celery or had developed directions for it. Also see https://www.healthycanning.com/canning-celery/</canningMethod>

            <freezingMethod>Celery loses its crispness when frozen. The frozen product is suitable only for cooked dishes.

                Preparation – Select crisp, tender stalks, free from coarse strings. Wash thoroughly, trim and cut stalks into l-inch lengths.

                Water blanch for 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-make-dehydrated-celery-1327565#:~:text=Arrange%20the%20celery%20pieces%20on,takes%206%20to%208%20hours.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.healthycanning.com/canning-celery/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/celery.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-make-dehydrated-celery-1327565#:~:text=Arrange%20the%20celery%20pieces%20on,takes%206%20to%208%20hours.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Corn</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 31½ pounds (in husk) of sweet corn is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 20 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 35 pounds and yields 6 to 11 quarts – an average of 4½ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select ears containing slightly immature kernels or of ideal quality for eating fresh. Canning of some sweeter varieties or too immature kernels may cause browning. Can a small amount, check color and flavor before canning large quantities.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Husk corn, remove silk, and wash. Blanch 3 minutes in boiling water. Cut corn from cob at about three-fourths the depth of kernel. Caution: Do not scrape cob.

                Hot pack – To each clean quart of kernels in a saucepan, add 1 cup of hot water, heat to boiling and simmer 5 minutes. Add 1 teaspoon of salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Fill jars with corn and cooking liquid, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Fill jars with raw kernels, leaving 1-inch headspace. Do not shake or press down. Add 1 teaspoon of salt per quart to the jar, if desired.

                Add fresh boiling water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according the the method of canning used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select only tender, freshly-gathered corn in the milk stage. Husk and trim the ears, remove silks and wash.

                Corn-on-the-cob – Water blanch small ears (1¼ inches or less in diameter) 7 minutes, medium ears (1¼ to 1½ inches in diameter) 9 minutes and large ears (over 1½ inches in diameter) 11 minutes. Cool promptly and completely to prevent a "cobby" taste. Drain and package. Seal and freeze.

                Whole Kernel Corn – Water blanch 4 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and cut from cob. Cut kernels from cob about 2/3 the depth of the kernels. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Cream Style Corn – Water blanch 4 minutes. Cool promptly and drain. Cut kernel tips and scrape the cobs with the back of a knife to remove the juice and the heart of the kernel. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Another way to prepare cream style corn for freezing is to cut and scrape the corn from the cob without blanching. Place the cut corn in a double boiler, and heat with constant stirring for about 10 minutes or until it thickens; allow to cool by placing the pan in ice water. Package in moisture-vapor resistant containers, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.gettystewart.com/how-to-dehydrate-corn/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/corn_kernel.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/corn.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.gettystewart.com/how-to-dehydrate-corn/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Cucumbers</name>
            <canningMethod>https://natashaskitchen.com/canned-dill-pickle-recipe/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/squash_summer.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.keyingredient.com/recipes/3465755032/3-recipes-for-dried-cucumbers/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://natashaskitchen.com/canned-dill-pickle-recipe/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/squash_summer.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.keyingredient.com/recipes/3465755032/3-recipes-for-dried-cucumbers/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Eggplant</name>
            <canningMethod>https://www.eatwell101.com/canned-eggplant-recipe</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Harvest before seeds become mature and when color is uniformly dark. Wash, peel and slice 1/3-inch thick. Prepare quickly, enough eggplant for one blanching at a time.

                Water blanch 4 minutes in 1 gallon of boiling water containing 1/2 cup lemon juice. Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                For Frying – Pack the drained slices with freezer wrap between slices. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://delishably.com/vegetable-dishes/How-to-Dry-Eggplant-An-Illustrated-Guide</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.eatwell101.com/canned-eggplant-recipe</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/eggplant.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://delishably.com/vegetable-dishes/How-to-Dry-Eggplant-An-Illustrated-Guide</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Garlic-in-Oil</name>
            <canningMethod>https://barefeetinthekitchen.com/preserving-garlic-for-winter/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Research performed by the National Center for Home Food Preservation confirmed that mixtures of garlic in oil stored at room temperature are at risk for the development of botulism.

                Garlic-in-oil should be made fresh and stored in the refrigerator at 40°F or lower for no more than 4 days. It may be frozen for long term storage for up to several months. Package in glass freezer jars or plastic freezer boxes, leaving ½-inch headspace. Label, date and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.garlicfarm.ca/garlic-drying.htm</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://barefeetinthekitchen.com/preserving-garlic-for-winter/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/garlic_oil.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.garlicfarm.ca/garlic-drying.htm</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Greens (including Spinach)</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/spinach_greens.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young, tender green leaves. Wash thoroughly and cut off woody stems. Water blanch collards 3 minutes and all other greens 2 minutes.

                Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://learn.eartheasy.com/articles/supercharge-your-meals-with-dehydrated-greens/#:~:text=To%20dehydrate%20the%20greens%2C%20place,the%20longer%20the%20drying%20time.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/spinach_greens.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/greens.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://learn.eartheasy.com/articles/supercharge-your-meals-with-dehydrated-greens/#:~:text=To%20dehydrate%20the%20greens%2C%20place,the%20longer%20the%20drying%20time.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Fresh Herbs</name>
            <canningMethod>https://canningdiva.com/canning-mint-jelly/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Wash, drain and pat dry with paper towels. Wrap a few sprigs or leaves in freezer wrap and place in a freezer bag. Seal and freeze.

                These can be chopped and used in cooked dishes. These usually are not suitable for garnish, as the frozen product becomes limp when it thaws.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruce.com/how-to-dry-and-store-herbs-1403397</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://canningdiva.com/canning-mint-jelly/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/herbs.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruce.com/how-to-dry-and-store-herbs-1403397</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Horseradish</name>
            <canningMethod>https://www.food.com/recipe/horseradish-canned-30959</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/broccoli.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.leaf.tv/articles/how-to-dry-horseradish-into-powder/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.food.com/recipe/horseradish-canned-30959</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/broccoli.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.leaf.tv/articles/how-to-dry-horseradish-into-powder/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Kohlrabi</name>
            <canningMethod>https://alexandracooks.com/2015/06/14/csa-week-1-anchovy-butter-pickled-kohlrabi-turnips-what-to-do-with-them/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select stems when fully grown but tender. Cut off tops and roots. Wash and peel off the tough bark. Leave whole or dice in 1/2 inch cubes. Water blanch whole 3 minutes and cubes 1 minute.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.onegreenplanet.org/vegan-recipe/kohlrabi-chips/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://alexandracooks.com/2015/06/14/csa-week-1-anchovy-butter-pickled-kohlrabi-turnips-what-to-do-with-them/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/kohlrabi.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.onegreenplanet.org/vegan-recipe/kohlrabi-chips/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Mushrooms</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/mushrooms.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Choose mushrooms free from spots and decay. Sort according to size. Wash thoroughly in cold water. Trim off ends of stems. If mushrooms are larger than 1 inch across, slice them or cut them into quarters.

                Mushrooms can be steamed or heated in fat in a fry pan. Steamed mushrooms will keep longer than those heated in fat.

                To Steam – Mushrooms to be steamed have better color if given anti-darkening treatment first. To do this, dip for 5 minutes in a solution containing 1 teaspoon lemon juice or 11/2 teaspoons citric acid to a pint of water.

                Then steam whole mushrooms 5 minutes, buttons or quarters 31/2 minutes and slices 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                To Heat in Fry Pan – Heat small quantities of mushrooms in margarine or butter in an open fry pan until almost done.

                Cool in air or set pan in which mushrooms were cooked in cold water. Pack into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://thewoksoflife.com/dried-mushrooms/#:~:text=Place%20in%20an%20oven%20heated%20to%20175%20degrees%20F%2F80,dried%20before%20sealing%20them%20away).</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/mushrooms.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/mushroom.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://thewoksoflife.com/dried-mushrooms/#:~:text=Place%20in%20an%20oven%20heated%20to%20175%20degrees%20F%2F80,dried%20before%20sealing%20them%20away).</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Okra</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/okra.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>The smooth type varieties freeze as well as or better than the ridged varieties because they do not split as easily. Preparation – Select young tender pods and separate into small pods (4 inches or under) and large pods. Wash. Remove the stems at the end of the seed cells, being careful not to expose the seed cell.

                Water blanch small pods 3 minutes and large pods 4 minutes.

                Cool promptly and drain. Leave whole or slice crosswise. Package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                For Frying – Wash and remove stems. blanch small pods 3 minutes and large pods 4 minutes. Cool promptly and drain. Slice crosswise and dredge with meal or flour. Spread in a single layer on shallow trays. Place in freezer just long enough to freeze firm. Package quickly, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.hgtv.com/outdoors/gardens/garden-to-table/spicy-dried-okra#:~:text=Scrub%20okra%2C%20rinse%20with%20cold,okra%20in%20a%20large%20bowl.&amp;text=Add%20salt%20and%20cayenne%20pepper%20and%20toss%20to%20coat.&amp;text=Dry%20until%20crisp%20and%20breakable,on%20dehydrator%20and%20okra%20size).</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/okra.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/okra.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.hgtv.com/outdoors/gardens/garden-to-table/spicy-dried-okra#:~:text=Scrub%20okra%2C%20rinse%20with%20cold,okra%20in%20a%20large%20bowl.&amp;text=Add%20salt%20and%20cayenne%20pepper%20and%20toss%20to%20coat.&amp;text=Dry%20until%20crisp%20and%20breakable,on%20dehydrator%20and%20okra%20size).</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Onions</name>
            <canningMethod>https://toriavey.com/toris-kitchen/pickled-red-onions/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Bulb onions store well in a cool, dry place. Freezing is usually not recommended for preserving whole onions, but see below if desired.

                Diced Onions – Peel, trim and clean thoroughly. Dice (about 1/4-inch pieces). No blanching is required. Either pack dry into recommended freezer bags or containers, leaving1/2-inch headspace.  Or, freeze separated pieces on a clean tray prior to packaging. Eliminate as much air as possible from the package for this method. Onions frozen this way are best used within a few months.

                Green Onions – Young green onions may be chopped for salads and cooking and frozen without blanching, but they will not be crisp. They will be highly flavored but may be slightly tough. They can be packaged by either of the methods above for diced onions.

                Whole Bulb Onions - Choose mature bulbs; peel, trim and clean thoroughly as for eating.
                Water blanch for 3 minutes (smaller onions) to 7 minutes (larger onions) or until center is completely heated.
                Cool promptly, drain well, and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze. These would be considered suitable for cooking only.

                Onion Rings – Wash, peel and slice onions. Separate slices into rings. Water blanch for 10 to 15 seconds. Cool promptly, drain and coat with flour. Dip in milk. Coat with a mixture of equal parts cornmeal and pancake mix. Arrange in a single layer on a tray. Freeze. Pack into containers using plastic wrap to separate the layers. No headspace is necessary. Seal and freeze.   To prepare, fry frozen rings in 375ºF oil until golden brown.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://growagoodlife.com/dehydrate-onions/#:~:text=Turn%20your%20onions%20into%20dehydrated%20onion%20flakes,dried%20onions%2C%20and%20onion%20powder.&amp;text=To%20dry%20the%20onions%3A,trays%20in%20a%20single%20layer.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://toriavey.com/toris-kitchen/pickled-red-onions/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/onion.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://growagoodlife.com/dehydrate-onions/#:~:text=Turn%20your%20onions%20into%20dehydrated%20onion%20flakes,dried%20onions%2C%20and%20onion%20powder.&amp;text=To%20dry%20the%20onions%3A,trays%20in%20a%20single%20layer.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peas Blackeye or Field</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peas_green_shelled.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select pods when seeds are tender and well-filled. Wash pods. Shell and discard over-mature and immature seeds and those injured by insects. Wash shelled peas.

                Water blanch 2 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2 inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://oureverydaylife.com/how-to-dehydrate-peas-12788346.html#:~:text=Place%20the%20peas%20on%20screens,to%20allow%20for%20even%20drying.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peas_green_shelled.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/peas_field.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://oureverydaylife.com/how-to-dehydrate-peas-12788346.html#:~:text=Place%20the%20peas%20on%20screens,to%20allow%20for%20even%20drying.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peas Green</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peas_green_shelled.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Harvest when pods are filled with young, tender peas that have not become starchy. Wash and shell; water blanch l1/2 minutes, cool and drain. Package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://oureverydaylife.com/how-to-dehydrate-peas-12788346.html#:~:text=Place%20the%20peas%20on%20screens,to%20allow%20for%20even%20drying.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peas_green_shelled.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/peas_green.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://oureverydaylife.com/how-to-dehydrate-peas-12788346.html#:~:text=Place%20the%20peas%20on%20screens,to%20allow%20for%20even%20drying.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peas Pods Edible (Sugar, Chinese, Snow Peas or Sugar Snap Peas)</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peas_green_shelled.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select bright green, flat, tender pods. Wash. Remove stems, blossom ends and any strings. Leave whole. Water blanch 11/2 minutes for small pods; 2 minutes for large pods. (NOTE: If the peas have started to develop, follow the directions for green beans. If the peas are already developed, shell and follow the directions for green peas.) Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://oureverydaylife.com/how-to-dehydrate-peas-12788346.html#:~:text=Place%20the%20peas%20on%20screens,to%20allow%20for%20even%20drying.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peas_green_shelled.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pea_pod.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://oureverydaylife.com/how-to-dehydrate-peas-12788346.html#:~:text=Place%20the%20peas%20on%20screens,to%20allow%20for%20even%20drying.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peppers Bell or Sweet</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peppers.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select crisp, tender, green or bright red pods. Wash, cut out stems, cut in half and remove seeds. If desired, cut into 1/2-inch strips or rings.

                Heated – Good for use in cooking. Water blanch halves 3 minutes, strips or rings 2 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Unheated – Good for use in uncooked foods because they have a crisper texture, or in cooked foods. Package raw, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://barefeetinthekitchen.com/dehydrated-bell-peppers/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/peppers.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pepper_bell.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://barefeetinthekitchen.com/dehydrated-bell-peppers/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peppers Hot</name>
            <canningMethod>https://www.thebossykitchen.com/how-to-preserve-hot-peppers-in-vinegar/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Wash and stem peppers. Package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.cayennediane.com/how-to-dry-peppers/#:~:text=Cut%20your%20peppers%20in%20half,least%20a%20couple%20of%20inches.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.thebossykitchen.com/how-to-preserve-hot-peppers-in-vinegar/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pepper_hot.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.cayennediane.com/how-to-dry-peppers/#:~:text=Cut%20your%20peppers%20in%20half,least%20a%20couple%20of%20inches.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Pimientos</name>
            <canningMethod>https://www.thebossykitchen.com/how-to-preserve-hot-peppers-in-vinegar/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, crisp pimientos of deep red color. Peel by roasting in oven 400 to 450ºF for 6 to 8 minutes or until skins can be rubbed off. Wash off the charred skins, cut out stems and remove seeds. Package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.food.com/recipe/homemade-paprika-494183</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.thebossykitchen.com/how-to-preserve-hot-peppers-in-vinegar/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pimento.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.food.com/recipe/homemade-paprika-494183</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Potatoes New Irish</name>
            <canningMethod>https://practicalselfreliance.com/canning-potatoes/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select smooth new potatoes directly from the garden. Peel or scrape and wash. Water blanch for 3 to 5 minutes, depending on the size.

                Cool, drain and package whole or sectioned, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                French Fried Potatoes – Select mature potatoes which have been stored 30 days. Wash, peel and cut into 1/3-inch sticks lengthwise, then crosswise into 3/8-inch strips. Rinse in cold water. Dry thoroughly. Fry small amounts in deep, hot fat (360ºF) about 5 minutes until tender but not brown. Drain on paper towel. Cool. Package, seal and freeze.

                At serving time, finish browning in a hot oven (475ºF).

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.gettystewart.com/dehydrating-potatoes/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://practicalselfreliance.com/canning-potatoes/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/potato_new.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.gettystewart.com/dehydrating-potatoes/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Potatoes Sweet</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/potato_sweet.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Choose medium to large sweet potatoes that have been cured for at least one week. Sort according to size and wash. Cook until almost tender in water, in steam, in a pressure cooker or in the oven. Let stand at room temperature until cool. Peel sweet potatoes, cut in halves, slice or mash.

                If desired, to prevent darkening, dip whole sweet potatoes or slices for 5 seconds in a solution of 1/2 cup lemon juice to 1 quart water.

                To keep mashed sweet potatoes from darkening, mix 2 tablespoons orange or lemon juice with each quart of mashed sweet potatoes.

                Pack into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Baked – Wash, trim and heat potatoes in oven at 350ºF without peeling until slightly soft. Cool, remove peel and wrap individually in aluminum foil. Place in polyethylene bags and freeze. Complete the baking in an oven at 350ºF immediately before serving, leaving the potatoes wrapped in foil.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.platingsandpairings.com/sweet-potato-dog-chews-7/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/potato_sweet.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/potato_sweet.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.platingsandpairings.com/sweet-potato-dog-chews-7/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Pumpkin</name>
            <canningMethod>https://www.theprairiehomestead.com/2014/10/how-to-can-pumpkin.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select full-colored mature pumpkin with fine texture. Wash, cut into cooking-size sections and remove seeds.

                Cook until soft in boiling water, in steam, in a pressure cooker or in an oven. Remove pulp from rind and mash. To cool, place pan containing pumpkin in cold water and stir occasionally. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://texashomesteader.com/dehydrate-pumpkin/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.theprairiehomestead.com/2014/10/how-to-can-pumpkin.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pumpkin.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://texashomesteader.com/dehydrate-pumpkin/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Rhubarb</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/rhubarb_stewed.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Choose firm, tender, well-colored stalks with good flavor and few fibers. Wash, trim and cut into lengths to fit the package. Heating rhubarb in boiling water for 1 minute and cooling promptly in cold water helps retain color and flavor.

                Dry Pack – Pack either raw or preheated rhubarb tightly into containers without sugar. Leave headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Syrup Pack – Pack either raw or preheated rhubarb tightly into containers, cover with cold 40 percent syrup. Leave headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.gettystewart.com/how_to_dehydrate_rhubarb/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/rhubarb_stewed.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/rhubarb.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.gettystewart.com/how_to_dehydrate_rhubarb/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Rutabagas</name>
            <canningMethod>https://www.healthycanning.com/canning-rutabaga/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young, medium-sized rutabagas. Cut off tops, wash and peel. Cubed – Cut into cubes and water blanch 3 minutes.

                Cool, drain and pack, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Mashed – Cut into chunks and cook until tender in boiling water. Drain, mash, cool and pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://countrifiedhicks.blogspot.com/2016/11/dehydrating-rutabagas.html#:~:text=To%20dehydrate%20a%20rutabaga%2C%20rinse%20them%20well%20and%20then%20peel%20them.&amp;text=Using%20a%20mandolin%20or%20sharp,about%201%2F8%22%20thick.&amp;text=Turn%20on%20your%20dehydrator%20to,are%20ready%20the%20next%20morning.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.healthycanning.com/canning-rutabaga/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/rutabaga.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://countrifiedhicks.blogspot.com/2016/11/dehydrating-rutabagas.html#:~:text=To%20dehydrate%20a%20rutabaga%2C%20rinse%20them%20well%20and%20then%20peel%20them.&amp;text=Using%20a%20mandolin%20or%20sharp,about%201%2F8%22%20thick.&amp;text=Turn%20on%20your%20dehydrator%20to,are%20ready%20the%20next%20morning.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Squash Summer
                (Cocozelle, Crookneck, Pattypan, Straightneck, White Scallop, Zucchini)</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/pumpkin_winter_squash.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Choose young squash with tender skin. Wash and cut in 1/2-inch slices. Water blanch 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Grated Zucchini (for Baking) – Choose young tender zucchini. Wash and grate. Steam blanch in small quantities 1 to 2 minutes until translucent. Pack in measured amounts into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Cool by placing the containers in cold water. Seal and freeze.

                If watery when thawed, discard the liquid before using the zucchini.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dehydrate-zucchini-and-summer-squash-1327567#:~:text=Set%20the%20dehydrator%20for%20135,transfer%20it%20to%20airtight%20containers.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/pumpkin_winter_squash.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/squash_summer.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dehydrate-zucchini-and-summer-squash-1327567#:~:text=Set%20the%20dehydrator%20for%20135,transfer%20it%20to%20airtight%20containers.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Squash Winter
                (Acorn, Banana, Buttercup, Butternut, Golden Delicious, Hubbard, Spaghetti)</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/pumpkin_winter_squash.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, mature squash with a hard rind. For spaghetti squash, mashing the cooked pulp is not necessary.

                Cook until soft in boiling water, in steam, in a pressure cooker or in an oven. Remove pulp from rind and mash. To cool, place pan containing winter squash in cold water and stir occasionally. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dehydrate-zucchini-and-summer-squash-1327567#:~:text=Set%20the%20dehydrator%20for%20135,transfer%20it%20to%20airtight%20containers.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/pumpkin_winter_squash.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/squash_winter.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dehydrate-zucchini-and-summer-squash-1327567#:~:text=Set%20the%20dehydrator%20for%20135,transfer%20it%20to%20airtight%20containers.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Tomatoes</name>
            <canningMethod>https://food52.com/recipes/347-grandma-s-canned-tomatoes</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, ripe tomatoes with deep red color.

                Raw – Wash and dip in boiling water for 30 seconds to loosen skins. Core and peel. Freeze whole or in pieces. Pack into containers, leaving l-inch headspace. Seal and freeze. Use only for cooking or seasoning as tomatoes will not be solid when thawed.

                Juice – Wash, sort and trim firm, vine-ripened tomatoes. Cut in quarters or eighths. Simmer 5 to 10 minutes. Press through a sieve. If desired, season with 1 teaspoon salt to each quart of juice. Pour into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Stewed – Remove stem ends, peel and quarter ripe tomatoes. Cover and cook until tender (10 to 20 minutes). Place pan containing tomatoes in cold water to cool. Pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.wholesomeyum.com/how-to-make-sun-dried-tomatoes-in-the-oven/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://food52.com/recipes/347-grandma-s-canned-tomatoes</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/tomato.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.wholesomeyum.com/how-to-make-sun-dried-tomatoes-in-the-oven/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Tomatoes Green</name>
            <canningMethod>https://food52.com/recipes/347-grandma-s-canned-tomatoes</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, sound green tomatoes. Wash, core, and slice 1/4-inch thick.

                For Frying – Pack the slices into containers with freezer wrap between the slices. Leave 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.wholesomeyum.com/how-to-make-sun-dried-tomatoes-in-the-oven/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://food52.com/recipes/347-grandma-s-canned-tomatoes</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/tomato_green.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.wholesomeyum.com/how-to-make-sun-dried-tomatoes-in-the-oven/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Turnips or Parsnips</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/spinach_greens.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select small to medium, firm turnips or parsnips that are tender and have a mild flavor. Wash, peel and cut into 1/2-inch cubes. Water blanch for 2 minutes. Cool promptly in cold water and drain. Pack into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze,

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/drying-turnips-in-a-dehydrator-1327548#:~:text=Once%20the%20turnips%20are%20cool,at%20150%20F%2F65%20C.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/spinach_greens.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/turnip.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/drying-turnips-in-a-dehydrator-1327548#:~:text=Once%20the%20turnips%20are%20cool,at%20150%20F%2F65%20C.</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Zucchini</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/mixed_vegetables.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/squash_summer.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.christinascucina.com/dried-zucchini-save-some-for-winter/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/mixed_vegetables.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/squash_summer.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.christinascucina.com/dried-zucchini-save-some-for-winter/</dryingUrl>
            <type>vegetable</type>
        </Food>
    </Vegetables>

    <Fruits>
        <Food>
            <name>Apples</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 19 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 12-1/4 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 48 pounds and yields 16 to 19 quarts-an average of 2-3/4 pounds per quart.
                Quality: Select apples that are juicy, crispy, and preferably both sweet and tart.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners and Using Boiling Water Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash, peel, and core apples. To prevent discoloration, slice apples into water containing ascorbic acid. Raw packs make poor quality products. Place drained slices in large saucepan and add 1 pint water or very light, light, or medium syrup per 5 pounds of sliced apples. Boil 5 minutes, stirring occasionally to prevent burning. Fill jars with hot slices and hot syrup or water, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Adjust lids and process.

                Processing directions for canning sliced apples in a boiling-water, a dial, or a weighted-gauge canner are given in Table 1, Table 2, and Table 3. Tables at URl</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Syrup Pack is preferred for apples to be used for uncooked desserts or fruit cocktail. A sugar or dry pack is good for pie making.

                Select full-flavored apples that are crisp and firm, not mealy in texture. Wash, peel and core. Slice medium apples into twelfths, large ones into sixteenths.

                Syrup Pack – Use cold 40 percent syrup. To prevent browning, add 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart of syrup.

                Slice apples directly into syrup in container starting with 1/2 cup syrup to a pint container. Press fruit down in containers and add enough syrup to cover. Leave headspace. Place a small piece of crumpled water-resistant paper on top to hold fruit down. Seal and freeze.

                Sugar Pack – To prevent darkening, dissolve 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid in 3 tablespoons water. Sprinkle over the fruit. Or, apple slices can be steam blanched for 11/2 to 2 minutes.

                Mix 1/2 cup sugar with 1 quart (1 1/4 pounds) of fruit. Pack apples into containers and press fruit down, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Dry Pack – Follow the directions for Sugar Pack, omitting the sugar. Treated apple slices can also be frozen first on a tray and then packed into containers as soon as they are frozen. For more information, see other unsweetened packs.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/homemade-oven-baked-apple-chips/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/apple_sliced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apple.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/homemade-oven-baked-apple-chips/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Apricots</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 16 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 10 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 50 pounds and yields 20 to 25 quarts-an average of 2¼ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select firm, well-colored mature fruit of ideal quality for eating fresh.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners and Using Boiling Water Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash fruit well if skins are not removed. (Optional procedure for removal of skins - Dip washed fruit in boiling water for 30 to 60 seconds until skins loosen. Dip quickly in cold water and slip off skins.) Cut prepared apricots in half, remove pits and slice if desired. To prevent darkening, keep peeled fruit in ascorbic acid solution. Prepare and boil a very light, light, or medium syrup or pack apricots in water, apple juice, or white grape juice.

                Raw packs make poor quality apricots.

                Hot pack – In a large saucepan place drained fruit in syrup, water, or juice and bring to boil. Fill jars with hot fruit and cooking liquid, leaving ½-inch headspace. Place halves in layers, cut side down.

                Raw pack – Fill jars with raw fruit, cut side down, and add hot water, juice, or syrup, leaving ½-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process.

                Processing directions for canning apricots in a boiling-water canner are given in Table 1.

                Processing directions for canning apricots in a dial or weighted-gauge canner are given in Table 2 and Table 3.Tables info in URL.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm, ripe, uniformly yellow apricots. Sort, wash, halve and pit. Peel and slice if desired. If apricots are not peeled, heat them in boiling water 1/2 minute to keep skins from toughening during freezing. Cool in cold water and drain.

                Syrup Pack – Use cold 40 percent syrup. For a better quality frozen product, add 3/4 teaspoon (2250 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart of syrup. Pack apricots directly into containers. Cover with syrup, leaving headspace. Place a small piece of crumpled water-resistant paper on top to hold fruit down. Seal and freeze.

                Sugar Pack – Before combining apricots with sugar, give the fruit the following treatment to prevent darkening:

                Dissolve 1/4 teaspoon (750 mg) ascorbic acid in 3 tablespoons cold water and sprinkle over 1 quart (7/8 pound) of fruit. Mix 1/2 cup sugar with each quart of fruit. Stir until sugar is dissolved. Pack apricots into containers and press down until fruit is covered with juice, leaving headspace. Place a small piece of crumpled water-resistant paper on top to hold fruit down. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Apricots#:~:text=Line%20a%20baking%20sheet%20with,to%20dry%20apricots%2C%20read%20on!</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/apricot_sliced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apricot.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Apricots#:~:text=Line%20a%20baking%20sheet%20with,to%20dry%20apricots%2C%20read%20on!</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Avocados</name>
            <canningMethod>Here’s a quick and easy pickling solution. Multiply by the number of avocados you have.

                Ingredients

                1 ripe but firm avocado
                4 tablespoons vinegar
                2 tablespoons water (optional)
                1 to 2 teaspoons sugar (or to taste)
                1/2 teaspoon salt (or to taste)
                (see variations below)

                Directions

                Choose firm but ripe avocados. Peel, pit, and slice or cube the avocado flesh.
                In a bowl large enough to hold the avocado pieces, stir together vinegar, water, sugar, and salt until sugar and salt are completely dissolved.
                Pour vinegar mixture over slices or cubes of avocado.
                Cover, refrigerate, and use within 3 days.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select avocados that yield to gentle pressure with rinds free from dark blemishes. Peel fruit, cut in half and remove pit.

                Avocados are best frozen as purée – unsweetened for salads and sandwiches, sweetened for other uses. Avocados are not satisfactorily frozen whole or sliced. For a better quality product, add 1/4 teaspoon (750 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart of purée or add 1 tablespoon lemon juice for each 2 avocados.

                Pack into container, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.dryingallfoods.com/dehydrating-avocado/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/2724-avocado-preserving-methods/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/avocado.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.dryingallfoods.com/dehydrating-avocado/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Bananas</name>
            <canningMethod>Bananas can be used as an ingredient in home canning, but they can’t be canned plain on their own.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select firm ripe bananas. Peel; mash thoroughly. Add 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid per cup of mashed banana. Package in moisture-vapor resistant container. Seal and freeze.

            </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://naturallyella.com/baked-banana-chips/#:~:text=Slice%20bananas%20into%201%2F16,out%2C%202%2D3%20hours.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.healthycanning.com/canning-bananas/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/banana.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://naturallyella.com/baked-banana-chips/#:~:text=Slice%20bananas%20into%201%2F16,out%2C%202%2D3%20hours.</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Berries</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select full-flavored, ripe berries. Remove leaves, stems and immature or defective berries.

                Dry Pack – Do not wash berries. Washing results in a tougher skinned product. Pack berries into containers, leaving headspace. Berries can also be frozen first on a tray and then packed into containers as soon as they are frozen. Seal and freeze. Wash before using.

                Crushed or Puréed – Wash the berries. Crush, press berries through a fine sieve, or purée in a blender or food processor. Mix 1 to 1 1/8 cups of sugar with each quart (2 pounds) of crushed berries or purée. Stir until sugar is dissolved. Pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://jomygosh.com/2015/01/easiest-way-to-dry-blueberries-ever/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/blueberry.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://jomygosh.com/2015/01/easiest-way-to-dry-blueberries-ever/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Cherries</name>
            <canningMethod>Sweet or Sour Cherries - Whole
                Quantity: An average of 17½ pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 11 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A lug weighs 25 pounds and yields 8 to 12 quarts – an average of 2½ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select bright, uniformly colored cherries that are mature (of ideal quality for eating fresh or cooking).

                Please read Using Pressure Canners and Using Boiling Water Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Stem and wash cherries. Remove pits if desired. If pitted, place cherries in water containing ascorbic acid to prevent stem-end discoloration. If canned unpitted, prick skins on opposite sides with a clean needle to prevent splitting. Cherries may be canned in water, apple juice, white-grape juice, or syrup. If syrup is desired, select and prepare preferred type as directed.Hot pack – In a large saucepan add ½ cup water, juice, or syrup for each quart of drained fruit and bring to boil. Fill jars with cherries and cooking liquid, leaving ½-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Add ½ cup hot water, juice, or syrup to each jar. Fill jars with drained cherries, shaking down gently as you fill. Add more hot liquid, leaving ½-inch headspace. Adjust lids and process.

                Processing directions for canning cherries in a boiling-water, a dial, or a weighted-gauge canner are given in Table 1, Table 2, and Table 3. Tables at URL</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select bright, fully ripened cherries of dark colored varieties. Wash, stem and pit.

                Syrup Pack – Use cold, 40 percent syrup. For a better quality product add 1/2 teaspoon (1500 mg) ascorbic acid to each quart syrup. Pack fruit and cover with syrup, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-cherries-dehydrator-method-1327532</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/cherry_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/cherry_sweet.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-cherries-dehydrator-method-1327532</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Chokecherries</name>
            <canningMethod>ChokeCherry Jelly

                Ingredients
                4 cups chokecherry juice
                1/4 cup of lemon juice
                1 1/2– 2 cups sugar OR 1 1/2 cups honey
                4 t. Pomona’s Pectin (like this)
                4 t. calcium water (included in Pomona’s pectin)

                Instructions
                Step 1: *How to Make Chokecherry Juice* If you have a juicer, use it! I don’t, so I use this method:
                Clean, wash, and remove stems from berries
                Place in a large pot filled with enough water to just cover the fruit
                Simmer 15-30 minutes until fruit softens
                Use a potato masher to mash the juice out
                Strain through a cheesecloth-lined colander or jelly strainer
                Save the juice and discard pulp/pits
                Step 2: Mix chokecherry juice, lemon juice, and 4 teaspoons calcium water in a pot
                Thoroughly mix sugar or honey in separate bowl with 4 teaspoons pectin &amp; set aside
                Step 3: Bring juice mixture to a boil
                Add pectin/sugar mixture, mix until completely incorporated, then return to a boil
                Remove from heat, get ready to place it in your sterilized canning jars
                Step 4: Fill the jars, leaving 1/4″ headspace
                Boil in a hot-water bath canner 10 minutes (add an extra minute for every 1,000 feet you are above sea level)</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select bright red, tree ripened cherries. Wash, stem and pit.

                Syrup Pack – Pack cherries into containers and cover with cold 50 per cent syrup. Leave headspace. Seal and freeze.

                Sugar Pack – To 1 quart (1 and 1/3 pounds) cherries add 3/4 cup sugar. Mix until sugar is dissolved. Pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://openprairie.sdstate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1485&amp;context=extension_extra#:~:text=Lay%20the%20patties%20on%20a,hot%2C%20soapy%20water%20and%20dried.&amp;text=Leave%20about%201%2F2%20inch,occur%20throughout%20the%20drying%20process.&amp;text=Chokecherry%20patties%20will%20take%2012%2D16%20hours%20to%20dry.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.theprairiehomestead.com/2012/08/how-to-make-chokecherry-jelly-low-sugar-and-honey-variations.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/cherry_sour.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://openprairie.sdstate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1485&amp;context=extension_extra#:~:text=Lay%20the%20patties%20on%20a,hot%2C%20soapy%20water%20and%20dried.&amp;text=Leave%20about%201%2F2%20inch,occur%20throughout%20the%20drying%20process.&amp;text=Chokecherry%20patties%20will%20take%2012%2D16%20hours%20to%20dry.</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Citrus Fruits</name> //lemon curd
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/lemon_curd.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/freezer_lemoncurd.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.trail.recipes/dehydrating123/dehydrating123-why-and-how-to-dehydrate-citrus-fruits/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/lemon_curd.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/freezer_lemoncurd.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.trail.recipes/dehydrating123/dehydrating123-why-and-how-to-dehydrate-citrus-fruits/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Crabapple</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/crab_apple_spiced.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apple.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://homecookedvegan.blogspot.com/2016/01/dehydrated-crab-apples.html</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/crab_apple_spiced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/apple.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://homecookedvegan.blogspot.com/2016/01/dehydrated-crab-apples.html</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Currants Figs</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/fig.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/fig.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Figs#:~:text=To%20dry%20figs%2C%20start%20by,for%20up%20to%2036%20hours.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/fig.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/fig.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.wikihow.com/Dry-Figs#:~:text=To%20dry%20figs%2C%20start%20by,for%20up%20to%2036%20hours.</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Grapes</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/grapes_whole.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/grape.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.seriouseats.com/recipes/2017/02/oven-dried-grapes-raisins-recipe.html</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/grapes_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/grape.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.seriouseats.com/recipes/2017/02/oven-dried-grapes-raisins-recipe.html</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Melons</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/green_mangoes.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/melon.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/888-how-to-dry-melon-slices/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/green_mangoes.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/melon.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/888-how-to-dry-melon-slices/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Mint/Herbs</name>
            <canningMethod>https://canningdiva.com/canning-mint-jelly/</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/herbs.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruce.com/how-to-dry-and-store-herbs-1403397</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://canningdiva.com/canning-mint-jelly/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/herbs.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruce.com/how-to-dry-and-store-herbs-1403397</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Peaches</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/peach_sliced.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/peach.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dry-peaches-in-a-dehydrator-1327526</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/peach_sliced.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/peach.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/dry-peaches-in-a-dehydrator-1327526</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Pears</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pear_halved.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-pears-in-dehydrator-1327580</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pear_halved.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/how-to-dry-pears-in-dehydrator-1327580</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Pineapple</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pineapple.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pineapple.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://selfproclaimedfoodie.com/oven-dried-pineapple/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/pineapple.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pineapple.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://selfproclaimedfoodie.com/oven-dried-pineapple/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Plums</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/plum_halved.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/plum.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://frugalfamilyhome.com/food/drying-foods/how-to-dry-plums</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/plum_halved.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/plum.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://frugalfamilyhome.com/food/drying-foods/how-to-dry-plums</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Quince</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/asian_pears.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Preserving-Apples-Pears-and-Quince.pdf</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/asian_pears.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/pear.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>http://www.homepreservingbible.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/Preserving-Apples-Pears-and-Quince.pdf</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Rhubarb</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/rhubarb_stewed.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/rhubarb.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://madaboutmacarons.com/dried-rhubarb-chips/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/rhubarb_stewed.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/rhubarb.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://madaboutmacarons.com/dried-rhubarb-chips/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Strawberries</name>
            <canningMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/strawberry.html</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/oven-dried-strawberries/</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_02/berries_whole.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/strawberry.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>https://www.shelovesbiscotti.com/oven-dried-strawberries/</dryingUrl>
            <type>fruit</type>
        </Food>

    </Fruits>

    <Meats>
        <Food>
            <name>Chicken</name>
            <canningMethod>Chicken or Rabbit

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Choose freshly killed and dressed, heathy animals. Large chickens are more flavorful than fryers. Dressed chicken should be chilled for 6 to 12 hours before canning. Dressed rabbits should be soaked 1 hour in water containing 1 tablespoon of salt per quart, and then rinsed. Remove excess fat. Cut the chicken or rabbit into its suitable size parts for fitting into your jars leaving required headspace. Can with or without bones. The hot pack is preferred for best liquid cover and quality during storage. Natural poultry fat and juices are usually not enough to cover the meat in raw packs.

                Hot pack – Boil, steam or bake meat until about two-thirds done. Add 1 teaspoon salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Fill jars with pieces and hot broth, leaving 1-1/4 inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Add 1 teaspoon salt per quart, if desired. Fill jars loosely with raw meat pieces, leaving 1-1/4 inch headspace. Do not add liquid.

                Adjust lids and process following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the canning method used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Select only high quality, fresh poultry to freeze. The tender young bird is best for roasting, frying and broiling. Choose the more flavorful older birds for braising or stewing.

                Package poultry in freezer paper or wrap using the drugstore or butcher wrap, or place in freezer bags. Storebought poultry needs to be over-wrapped before freezing because its clear wrap is not moisture-vapor resistant. When packaging pieces, arrange them to form a compact, square, flat package so they will stack better in the freezer. After packaging, seal and freeze immediately.

                Quail, dove, duck, pheasant and other game birds should be dressed and gutted as soon as possible after shooting. Cool and clean properly. Remove excess fat on wild ducks and geese since it becomes rancid very quickly. Freeze as directed for poultry.

                Do not stuff poultry or game birds before freezing them. During freezing or thawing times, bacteria that cause foodborne illness could easily grow in the stuffing. Commercially stuffed frozen poultry is prepared under special safety conditions that cannot be duplicated at home.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>No links available.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_05/chicken_rabbit.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/poultry.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>No links available.</dryingUrl>
            <type>meat</type>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Red Meat</name>
            <canningMethod>(Hot Pack Method for Canning Meat)

                Beef, venison, elk, or pork; Salt (optional); Water; Canning jars, lids, and rings (quarts or pints are fine); A pressure canner
                Trim the meat to remove excess fat and gristle. (I usually try to do this when the meat is half-frozen. It makes the trimming much easier) Slice into strips against the grain, and then cut into roughly 1″ cubes (just eyeball it– no need to be exact). how to can beef, venison, or elk with a pressure canner for fork-tender meat! Place the cubes into a large stockpot and brown thoroughly on all sides. If your meat is especially lean, you may need to add a bit of fat (such as bacon grease, lard, or coconut oil) to the pan to prevent stickage. (Yes, that’s a word) The goal here is to simply brown the cubes— you don’t need to cook them all the way through.

                Canning Meat Tutorial
                Place the browned meat cubes into clean glass jars, leaving 1″ headspace. If using quart jars, add 1 teaspoon of salt. If using pint jars, add 1/2 teaspoon of salt. Canning Meat Tutorial: how to can beef, venison, or elk with a pressure canner for fork-tender meat! Pour water (how much you need will depend on how many jars you are canning) into the pot you used to brown the meat, and bring it to a boil. This will capture all the lovely bits from the bottom of the pot and create extra flavor in your finished product. Ladle the boiling water over the meat in the jars, leaving 1″ headspace. Wipe the rims, adjust the lids/rings, and process in a steam pressure canner as follows:

                Pints: 75 minutes
                Quarts: 90 minutes
                Use 10 pounds of pressure, UNLESS you are 1,000 feet or more above sea level. If that is the case, increase to 15 pounds of pressure.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Cutting steaks from a big piece of meat like a strip loin or a boneless rib roast
                allows you to make steaks just the right thickness. Grill some of the steaks now and freeze the
                remaining ones for another day. Here's how: The key to freezing a steak properly is to prevent
                air from touching the surface of the meat. Wrap each steak individually with plastic wrap, not
                butcher paper or aluminum foil, and seal it as tightly as possible. Place the wrapped steaks in a
                resealable freezer bag and set the freezer as close to 0°F as it will go. The colder, the better.
                Steaks packaged this way will keep very well for about 3 months. </freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>No links available.</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.theprairiehomestead.com/2015/01/canning-meat.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://www.weber.com/CA/en/grill-skills/mastering-red-meat/steak/freezing-steaks/weber-34455.html#:~:text=Wrap%20each%20steak%20individually%20with,well%20for%20about%203%20months.</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl>No links available.</dryingUrl>
            <type>meat</type>
        </Food>
      <Food>
        <name>Fish</name>
        <canningMethod>Gather your canning supplies: Pressure canner,canning jars, canning lids and rings jar lifter and canning funnel, stock pot, bowls, large spoons, sharp knife, towels and dish clothes.

            Ingredients: Fish, Canning salt
            First, clean your fish. You'll need to remove the head, tail, and all fins and scales. Wash well and split fish lengthwise. Cut fish into jar-length pieces.

            Large piece of fish. Washing fish. Cutting fish. Soak your fish in a salty brine for 1 hour. Use 1 cup of salt to 1 gallon of water. (This technique came from my Ball Blue Book, and I would think that brining would be especially helpful for flavor if the fish is fresh caught.)

            While fish is soaking, gather all materials needed. Start your water heating in your canner. See pressure canning for more detailed instructions.

            Drain fish for 10 minutes. You want to be sure it is well drained. Draining fish. Packing jars. Pack fish into hot jars (pints or half pints), skin sides out next to the glass. Leave a 1-inch headspace. Do not add liquid. Place lids and process according to pressure canning instructions.

            Process pints or half pints 1 hour 40 minutes at 10 pounds pressure.</canningMethod>
        <freezingMethod>Fresh fish is a tasty protein that has a relatively short shelf life. Any fish you are not planning on eating within a few days must be frozen. Properly freezing a fish does not mean tossing it into the freezer. Here's what you need to know to have top-quality fish for months:

            Air is your enemy. Any air that touches your fish will destroy it. It's that simple. So you must prevent air from contacting the fish by vacuum-sealing it, glazing it or wrapping it tightly. (This is in order of preference.)
            If you catch a lot of fish or buy lots of fresh fish from the market, buy a vacuum sealer. They're worth every penny and you'll use them frequently.
            If you choose not to vacuum seal, you can glaze the fish by dipping them in cold water and putting the dipped fish on a sheet pan in the freezer. Let that water freeze, then repeat the process several more times to get a 1/4 inch thick ice glaze on the fish. You can then put your glazed fish into a plastic bag and place in the freezer for storage.
            You can wrap your fish in plastic wrap, then put the wrapped fish into a plastic bag. This method is not as effective at preventing moisture loss and freezer burn like the other methods.</freezingMethod>
        <dryingMethod>No links available.</dryingMethod>
        <canningUrl>https://www.simplycanning.com/canning-fish.html</canningUrl>
        <freezingUrl>https://www.thespruceeats.com/tips-on-freezing-fish-1300632</freezingUrl>
        <dryingUrl>No links available.</dryingUrl>
        <type>meat</type>
    </Food>
    </Meats>
</resources>