<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <Tutorials>
        <String>https://nchfp.uga.edu/publications/uga/using_press_canners.html</String>
        <String>https://nchfp.uga.edu/publications/usda/GUIDE01_HomeCan_rev0715.pdf</String>
    </Tutorials>

    <Vegetables>
        <Food>
            <name>Artichokes</name>
            <canningMethod>This kitchen project delivers both flavor and texture unlike any store-bought artichokes. Home-canned, marinated artichoke hearts liven up pizza, a salad or a sandwich.

                Beware: The tannins in raw artichoke will stain your hands. Lemon juice will remove the stain.

                You'll need 3 sanitized pint jars with new lids and rings; see the NOTE, below.

                Make Ahead: The artichokes need 1 month to cure, during which time their texture changes from firm to velvety while their structure is retained. If you choose to skip the water-bath canning called for here, refrigerate the sealed jars of artichokes for 1 month before serving. (Artichokes that are not water-bath-canned will not achieve the same silky texture as those that are.) The water-bath-canned jars of artichokes need to cool for 12 hours. They are shelf stable for 1 year. Once opened, the jars should be refrigerated and used within a month.SERVINGS: 9 - 15

                Yield: (makes 3 pints)

                INGREDIENTS
                4 lemons
                9 medium or 15 baby artichokes
                1/4 cup plus 3 teaspoons kosher salt or sea salt
                1 cup distilled white vinegar, plus more as needed
                1/4 cup white wine vinegar
                1/4 cup mild olive oil, or more as needed
                1 tablespoon dried oregano
                3/4 teaspoon crushed red pepper flakes
                3 cloves garlic, root ends trimmed
                Three 1-inch strips lemon zest

                DIRECTIONS
                Halve and juice the lemons. Place the spent lemon halves in a 5-quart nonreactive (not aluminum or copper) pot; fill it with cold water. Strain and reserve the juice for the marinade.

                To trim the artichokes, pull the leaves from each one, snapping them where they naturally break. Use a sharp knife or vegetable peeler to peel the choke, then make a clean cut across the end of the stem, retaining the tender portion. Use a grapefruit spoon, melon baller or side of a teaspoon to scrape away the fuzzy choke, revealing the meaty part of it, then quarter the entire choke. (For baby artichokes, trim only to any inner leaves without a thorn.) As each choke is trimmed, drop it into the pot.

                Add 1/4 cup of salt. Bring the pot filled with lemon water and artichokes to a boil over high heat, then reduce the heat to medium or medium-low so the water is barely bubbling. Cook, uncovered, until fork-tender, about 10 minutes.

                Meanwhile, make the marinade: Combine the reserved lemon juice, vinegars, oil, oregano, crushed red pepper flakes and garlic cloves in a small saucepan over high heat. Bring to a boil; cook for 5 minutes, then remove from the heat.

                Use a slotted spoon to transfer the artichokes to the sanitized jars, dividing evenly and stacking the small ones and first cutting the medium ones into quarters. Tuck them in as tightly as possible without breaking or bruising.

                Whisk the marinade well and divide among the jars. If there is not enough marinade to cover, add oil as needed to leave 1/2 inch headspace at the top of each jar. Make sure 1 garlic clove, 1 strip of lemon zest and 1 teaspoon salt goes into each jar.

                Run a chopstick or flat plastic knife along the inside of the jar to remove any air bubbles. Clean the rim of each jar with distilled white vinegar to cut residual oils, place the warmed lids on and finger-tighten the rings (not too tight). Process in the boiling water bath for 15 minutes (see NOTE, below). Turn off the heat and let the jars rest in the pot for 10 minutes. Use tongs to transfer the jars to a clean, folded dish towel to cool over several hours.

                Store the water-bath-canned jars in a cool space to cure for 1 month.

                NOTE: Water-bath canning safely seals high acid, low pH foods in jars. The time for processing in the water-bath is calculated based on the size of the jar and the consistency and density of the food. For safety's sake, do not alter the jar size, ingredients, ratios or processing time in any canning recipes. If moved to change any of these items, simply put the prepared food in the refrigerator and eat within a week.

                Fill a large canning kettle or deep stockpot two-thirds full with water. To keep the jars from rattling against the pot, place a rack in the pot (a cake rack works well, or a folded dish towel is equally effective). Sanitize the jars in a short dishwasher cycle or by boiling them in a canning kettle or pot for 10 minutes. Fill a small saucepan with water and add the rings. Bring to a boil over high heat, slip in the lids and turn off the heat.

                Use a jar lifter or tongs to lower the filled, sealed jars upright into the boiling water-bath. When all the jars are in place, the water should be 1 to 2 inches above the top of the jar. Add water as needed. Bring the water to a low boil before starting the timer for processing.

                At the end of processing, turn off the heat and let the jars sit in the water bath until the boiling has stopped. This will reduce siphoning -- when the food burbles up under the lid, breaking the seal. Use the jar lifter or tongs to transfer the jars to a folded towel, placed upright. Leave the jars until they have completely cooled, at least 12 hours. Remove the rings and test the seal by lifting the jar by the lid. The lid should hold fast. Label and store in a cool, dry, dark space.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select those with uniformly green color, compact globes and tightly adhering leaves. Remove all leaves and choke or fuzzy portion. The portion that is left at the base is the heart. Cut away the stem just below the heart and trim any woody portions. Wash hearts in cold water and drain.

                Water blanch 7 minutes. Cook, drain and pack, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://www.washingtonpost.com/recipes/home-canned-artichoke-hearts/14027/</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/artichoke.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Asparagus</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 24½ pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 16 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A crate weighs 31 pounds and yields 7 to 12 quarts--an average of 3½ pounds per quart.

                Quality: Use tender, tight-tipped spears, 4 to 6 inches long.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash asparagus and trim off tough scales. Break off tough stems and wash again. Cut into 1-inch pieces or can whole.

                Hot pack – Cover asparagus with boiling water. Boil 2 or 3 minutes. Loosely fill jars with hot asparagus, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Fill jars with raw asparagus, packing as tightly as possible without crushing, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Add 1 teaspoon of salt per quart to the jars, if desired. Add boiling water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process as recommended in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the method of canning used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young tender spears. Wash thoroughly and sort into sizes. Trim stalks by removing scales with a sharp knife. Cut into even lengths to fit containers.

                Water blanch small spears 2 minutes, medium spears 3 minutes and large spears 4 minutes.

                Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/asparagus.html</dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/asparagus_spears.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl></freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name>Beans: Green, Snap, or Wax</name>
            <canningMethod>Quantity: An average of 14 pounds is needed per canner load of 7 quarts; an average of 9 pounds is needed per canner load of 9 pints. A bushel weighs 30 pounds and yields 12 to 20 quarts – an average of 2 pounds per quart.

                Quality: Select filled but tender, crisp pods. Remove and discard diseased and rusty pods.

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Wash beans and trim ends. Leave whole or cut or snap into 1-inch pieces.

                Hot pack –Cover with boiling water; boil 5 minutes. Fill jars loosely with beans, leaving 1-inch headspace. Add 1 teaspoon of canning salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Cover beans with hot cooking liquid, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Fill jars tightly with raw beans, leaving 1-inch headspace. Add 1 teaspoon of canning salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Add boiling water, leaving 1-inch headspace.

                Adjust lids and process in a pressure canner following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the type of canner being used. (There is no safe option for processing green beans in a boiling water canner.)</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Preparation – Select young tender pods when the seed is first formed. Wash in cold water, snip and cut into 2 to 4-inch lengths.

                Water blanch 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_04/beans_snap_italian.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/bean_green.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name></name>
            <canningMethod></canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod></freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl></canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl></freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
    </Vegetables>

    <Fruits>
        <Food>
            <name></name>
            <canningMethod></canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod></freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl></canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl></freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name></name>
            <canningMethod></canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod></freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl></canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl></freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>

    </Fruits>

    <Meats>
        <Food>
            <name>Chicken</name>
            <canningMethod>Chicken or Rabbit

                Please read Using Pressure Canners before beginning. If this is your first time canning, it is recommended that you read Principles of Home Canning.

                Procedure: Choose freshly killed and dressed, heathy animals. Large chickens are more flavorful than fryers. Dressed chicken should be chilled for 6 to 12 hours before canning. Dressed rabbits should be soaked 1 hour in water containing 1 tablespoon of salt per quart, and then rinsed. Remove excess fat. Cut the chicken or rabbit into its suitable size parts for fitting into your jars leaving required headspace. Can with or without bones. The hot pack is preferred for best liquid cover and quality during storage. Natural poultry fat and juices are usually not enough to cover the meat in raw packs.

                Hot pack – Boil, steam or bake meat until about two-thirds done. Add 1 teaspoon salt per quart to the jar, if desired. Fill jars with pieces and hot broth, leaving 1-1/4 inch headspace.

                Raw pack – Add 1 teaspoon salt per quart, if desired. Fill jars loosely with raw meat pieces, leaving 1-1/4 inch headspace. Do not add liquid.

                Adjust lids and process following the recommendations in Table 1 or Table 2 according to the canning method used.</canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod>Select only high quality, fresh poultry to freeze. The tender young bird is best for roasting, frying and broiling. Choose the more flavorful older birds for braising or stewing.

                Package poultry in freezer paper or wrap using the drugstore or butcher wrap, or place in freezer bags. Storebought poultry needs to be over-wrapped before freezing because its clear wrap is not moisture-vapor resistant. When packaging pieces, arrange them to form a compact, square, flat package so they will stack better in the freezer. After packaging, seal and freeze immediately.

                Quail, dove, duck, pheasant and other game birds should be dressed and gutted as soon as possible after shooting. Cool and clean properly. Remove excess fat on wild ducks and geese since it becomes rancid very quickly. Freeze as directed for poultry.

                Do not stuff poultry or game birds before freezing them. During freezing or thawing times, bacteria that cause foodborne illness could easily grow in the stuffing. Commercially stuffed frozen poultry is prepared under special safety conditions that cannot be duplicated at home.</freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/can_05/chicken_rabbit.html</canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl>https://nchfp.uga.edu/how/freeze/poultry.html</freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
        <Food>
            <name></name>
            <canningMethod></canningMethod>
            <freezingMethod></freezingMethod>
            <dryingMethod></dryingMethod>
            <canningUrl></canningUrl>
            <freezingUrl></freezingUrl>
            <dryingUrl></dryingUrl>
        </Food>
    </Meats>
    <!--<string-array name="vegetables">
        <item>Artichokes</item>
        <item>Asparagus</item>
        <item>Beans: Green, Snap, or Wax</item>
        <item>Beans: Lima, Butter, or Pinto</item>
        <item>Beets</item>
        <item>Broccoli</item>
        <item>Brussels Sprouts</item>
        <item>Cabbage or Chinese Cabbage</item>
        <item>Carrots</item>
        <item>Cauliflower</item>
        <item>Celery</item>
        <item>Corn</item>
        <item>Eggplant</item>
        <item>Greens (Including Spinach)</item>
        <item>Garlic-in-Oil</item>
        <item>Fresh Herbs</item>
        <item>Kohlrabi</item>
        <item>Mushroom</item>
        <item>Okra</item>
        <item>Onions</item>
        <item>Edible Pod Peas (Sugar, Chinese, Snow Peas or Sugar Snap Peas)</item>
        <item>Blackeye or Field Peas</item>
        <item>Green Peas</item>
        <item>Bell or Sweet Peppers</item>
        <item>Hot Peppers</item>
        <item>Pimientos</item>
        <item>New Irish Potatoes</item>
        <item>Sweet Potatoes</item>
        <item>Pumpkin</item>
        <item>Rhubarb</item>
        <item>Rhutabagas</item>
        <item>Chayote Squash (Vegetable Pear)</item>
        <item>Summer Squash
(Cocozelle, Crookneck, Pattypan, Straightneck, White Scallop, Zucchini)</item>
        <item>Winter Squash
(Acorn, Banana, Buttercup, Butternut, Golden Delicious, Hubbard, Spaghetti)</item>
        <item>Tomatoes</item>
        <item>Green Tomatoes</item>
        <item>Turnips or Parsnips</item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
    </string-array>


    <string-array name="vegetables_freezing">
        <item>Preparation – Select those with uniformly green color, compact globes and tightly adhering leaves. Remove all leaves and choke or fuzzy portion. The portion that is left at the base is the heart. Cut away the stem just below the heart and trim any woody portions. Wash hearts in cold water and drain.

Water blanch 7 minutes. Cook, drain and pack, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select young tender spears. Wash thoroughly and sort into sizes. Trim stalks by removing scales with a sharp knife. Cut into even lengths to fit containers.

Water blanch small spears 2 minutes, medium spears 3 minutes and large spears 4 minutes.

Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select young tender pods when the seed is first formed. Wash in cold water, snip and cut into 2 to 4-inch lengths.

Water blanch 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Harvest while the seed is in the green stage. Wash, shell and sort according to size.

Water blanch small beans 2 minutes, medium beans 3 minutes and large beans 4 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select deep, uniformly-red, tender, young beets. Wash and sort according to size. Trim tops, leaving 1/2 inch of stems and tap root, to prevent bleeding of color during cooking.

Cook in boiling water until tender-for small beets 25 to 30 minutes; for medium beets 45 to 50 minutes.

Cool promptly in cold water. Peel, remove stem and tap root, and cut into slices or cubes. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select firm, young, tender stalks with compact heads. Remove leaves and woody portions. Separate heads into convenient-size sections and immerse in brine (4 teaspoons salt to 1 gallon water) for 30 minutes to remove insects. Split lengthwise so flowerets are no more than 1 1/2 inches across.

Water blanch 3 minutes in boiling water or steam blanch 5 minutes.

Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select green, firm and compact heads. Examine heads carefully to make sure they are free from insects. Trim, removing coarse outer leaves. Wash thoroughly. Sort into small, medium and large sizes.

Water blanch small heads 3 minutes, medium heads 4 minutes and large heads 5 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Frozen cabbage or Chinese cabbage are suitable for use only as a cooked vegetable.

Select freshly picked, solid heads. Trim coarse outer leaves from head. Cut into medium to coarse shreds or thin wedges, or separate head into leaves. Water blanch 1½ minutes.

Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select young, tender, coreless, medium length carrots. Remove tops, wash and peel. Leave small carrots whole. Cut others into thin slices, 1/4-inch cubes or lengthwise strips.

Water blanch small whole carrots 5 minutes, diced or sliced 2 minutes and lengthwise strips 2 minutes.

Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Choose compact white heads. Trim off leaves and cut head into pieces about 1 inch across. If necessary to remove insects, soak for 30 minutes in solution of salt and water (4 teaspoons salt per gallon water). Drain.

Water blanch for 3 minutes in water containing 4 teaspoons salt per gallon water.

Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Celery loses its crispness when frozen. The frozen product is suitable only for cooked dishes.

Preparation – Select crisp, tender stalks, free from coarse strings. Wash thoroughly, trim and cut stalks into l-inch lengths.

Water blanch for 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select only tender, freshly-gathered corn in the milk stage. Husk and trim the ears, remove silks and wash.

Corn-on-the-cob – Water blanch small ears (1¼ inches or less in diameter) 7 minutes, medium ears (1¼ to 1½ inches in diameter) 9 minutes and large ears (over 1½ inches in diameter) 11 minutes. Cool promptly and completely to prevent a "cobby" taste. Drain and package. Seal and freeze.

Whole Kernel Corn – Water blanch 4 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and cut from cob. Cut kernels from cob about 2/3 the depth of the kernels. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

Cream Style Corn – Water blanch 4 minutes. Cool promptly and drain. Cut kernel tips and scrape the cobs with the back of a knife to remove the juice and the heart of the kernel. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

Another way to prepare cream style corn for freezing is to cut and scrape the corn from the cob without blanching. Place the cut corn in a double boiler, and heat with constant stirring for about 10 minutes or until it thickens; allow to cool by placing the pan in ice water. Package in moisture-vapor resistant containers, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Harvest before seeds become mature and when color is uniformly dark. Wash, peel and slice 1/3-inch thick. Prepare quickly, enough eggplant for one blanching at a time.

Water blanch 4 minutes in 1 gallon of boiling water containing 1/2 cup lemon juice. Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

For Frying – Pack the drained slices with freezer wrap between slices. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select young, tender green leaves. Wash thoroughly and cut off woody stems. Water blanch collards 3 minutes and all other greens 2 minutes.

Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Research performed by the National Center for Home Food Preservation confirmed that mixtures of garlic in oil stored at room temperature are at risk for the development of botulism.

Garlic-in-oil should be made fresh and stored in the refrigerator at 40°F or lower for no more than 4 days. It may be frozen for long term storage for up to several months. Package in glass freezer jars or plastic freezer boxes, leaving ½-inch headspace. Label, date and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Wash, drain and pat dry with paper towels. Wrap a few sprigs or leaves in freezer wrap and place in a freezer bag. Seal and freeze.

These can be chopped and used in cooked dishes. These usually are not suitable for garnish, as the frozen product becomes limp when it thaws.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select stems when fully grown but tender. Cut off tops and roots. Wash and peel off the tough bark. Leave whole or dice in 1/2 inch cubes. Water blanch whole 3 minutes and cubes 1 minute.

Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Choose mushrooms free from spots and decay. Sort according to size. Wash thoroughly in cold water. Trim off ends of stems. If mushrooms are larger than 1 inch across, slice them or cut them into quarters.

Mushrooms can be steamed or heated in fat in a fry pan. Steamed mushrooms will keep longer than those heated in fat.

To Steam – Mushrooms to be steamed have better color if given anti-darkening treatment first. To do this, dip for 5 minutes in a solution containing 1 teaspoon lemon juice or 11/2 teaspoons citric acid to a pint of water.

Then steam whole mushrooms 5 minutes, buttons or quarters 31/2 minutes and slices 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

To Heat in Fry Pan – Heat small quantities of mushrooms in margarine or butter in an open fry pan until almost done.

Cool in air or set pan in which mushrooms were cooked in cold water. Pack into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>The smooth type varieties freeze as well as or better than the ridged varieties because they do not split as easily.
Preparation – Select young tender pods and separate into small pods (4 inches or under) and large pods. Wash. Remove the stems at the end of the seed cells, being careful not to expose the seed cell.

Water blanch small pods 3 minutes and large pods 4 minutes.

Cool promptly and drain. Leave whole or slice crosswise. Package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

For Frying – Wash and remove stems. blanch small pods 3 minutes and large pods 4 minutes. Cool promptly and drain. Slice crosswise and dredge with meal or flour. Spread in a single layer on shallow trays. Place in freezer just long enough to freeze firm. Package quickly, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Bulb onions store well in a cool, dry place. Freezing is usually not recommended for preserving whole onions, but see below if desired.

Diced Onions – Peel, trim and clean thoroughly. Dice (about 1/4-inch pieces). No blanching is required. Either pack dry into recommended freezer bags or containers, leaving1/2-inch headspace.  Or, freeze separated pieces on a clean tray prior to packaging. Eliminate as much air as possible from the package for this method. Onions frozen this way are best used within a few months.

Green Onions – Young green onions may be chopped for salads and cooking and frozen without blanching, but they will not be crisp. They will be highly flavored but may be slightly tough. They can be packaged by either of the methods above for diced onions.

Whole Bulb Onions - Choose mature bulbs; peel, trim and clean thoroughly as for eating.
Water blanch for 3 minutes (smaller onions) to 7 minutes (larger onions) or until center is completely heated.
Cool promptly, drain well, and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze. These would be considered suitable for cooking only.

Onion Rings – Wash, peel and slice onions. Separate slices into rings. Water blanch for 10 to 15 seconds. Cool promptly, drain and coat with flour. Dip in milk. Coat with a mixture of equal parts cornmeal and pancake mix. Arrange in a single layer on a tray. Freeze. Pack into containers using plastic wrap to separate the layers. No headspace is necessary. Seal and freeze.   To prepare, fry frozen rings in 375ºF oil until golden brown.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select bright green, flat, tender pods. Wash. Remove stems, blossom ends and any strings. Leave whole. Water blanch 11/2 minutes for small pods; 2 minutes for large pods. (NOTE: If the peas have started to develop, follow the directions for green beans. If the peas are already developed, shell and follow the directions for green peas.) Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select pods when seeds are tender and well-filled. Wash pods. Shell and discard over-mature and immature seeds and those injured by insects. Wash shelled peas.

Water blanch 2 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2 inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Harvest when pods are filled with young, tender peas that have not become starchy. Wash and shell; water blanch l1/2 minutes, cool and drain. Package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select crisp, tender, green or bright red pods. Wash, cut out stems, cut in half and remove seeds. If desired, cut into 1/2-inch strips or rings.

Heated – Good for use in cooking. Water blanch halves 3 minutes, strips or rings 2 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

Unheated – Good for use in uncooked foods because they have a crisper texture, or in cooked foods. Package raw, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Wash and stem peppers. Package, leaving no headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select firm, crisp pimientos of deep red color. Peel by roasting in oven 400 to 450ºF for 6 to 8 minutes or until skins can be rubbed off. Wash off the charred skins, cut out stems and remove seeds. Package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select smooth new potatoes directly from the garden. Peel or scrape and wash. Water blanch for 3 to 5 minutes, depending on the size.

Cool, drain and package whole or sectioned, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

French Fried Potatoes – Select mature potatoes which have been stored 30 days. Wash, peel and cut into 1/3-inch sticks lengthwise, then crosswise into 3/8-inch strips. Rinse in cold water. Dry thoroughly. Fry small amounts in deep, hot fat (360ºF) about 5 minutes until tender but not brown. Drain on paper towel. Cool. Package, seal and freeze.

At serving time, finish browning in a hot oven (475ºF).</item>
        <item>Preparation – Choose medium to large sweet potatoes that have been cured for at least one week. Sort according to size and wash. Cook until almost tender in water, in steam, in a pressure cooker or in the oven. Let stand at room temperature until cool. Peel sweet potatoes, cut in halves, slice or mash.

If desired, to prevent darkening, dip whole sweet potatoes or slices for 5 seconds in a solution of 1/2 cup lemon juice to 1 quart water.

To keep mashed sweet potatoes from darkening, mix 2 tablespoons orange or lemon juice with each quart of mashed sweet potatoes.

Pack into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

Baked – Wash, trim and heat potatoes in oven at 350ºF without peeling until slightly soft. Cool, remove peel and wrap individually in aluminum foil. Place in polyethylene bags and freeze. Complete the baking in an oven at 350ºF immediately before serving, leaving the potatoes wrapped in foil.

</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select full-colored mature pumpkin with fine texture. Wash, cut into cooking-size sections and remove seeds.

Cook until soft in boiling water, in steam, in a pressure cooker or in an oven. Remove pulp from rind and mash. To cool, place pan containing pumpkin in cold water and stir occasionally. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Choose firm, tender, well-colored stalks with good flavor and few fibers. Wash, trim and cut into lengths to fit the package. Heating rhubarb in boiling water for 1 minute and cooling promptly in cold water helps retain color and flavor.

Dry Pack – Pack either raw or preheated rhubarb tightly into containers without sugar. Leave headspace. Seal and freeze.

Syrup Pack – Pack either raw or preheated rhubarb tightly into containers, cover with cold 40 percent syrup. Leave headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select young, medium-sized rutabagas. Cut off tops, wash and peel. Cubed – Cut into cubes and water blanch 3 minutes.

Cool, drain and pack, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

Mashed – Cut into chunks and cook until tender in boiling water. Drain, mash, cool and pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select those with tender skins. Wash, remove stem and blossom end. Do not pare. Dice, removing seed. Water blanch 2 minutes.

Cool, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Choose young squash with tender skin. Wash and cut in 1/2-inch slices. Water blanch 3 minutes. Cool promptly, drain and package, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.

Grated Zucchini (for Baking) – Choose young tender zucchini. Wash and grate. Steam blanch in small quantities 1 to 2 minutes until translucent. Pack in measured amounts into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Cool by placing the containers in cold water. Seal and freeze.

If watery when thawed, discard the liquid before using the zucchini.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select firm, mature squash with a hard rind. For spaghetti squash, mashing the cooked pulp is not necessary.

Cook until soft in boiling water, in steam, in a pressure cooker or in an oven. Remove pulp from rind and mash. To cool, place pan containing winter squash in cold water and stir occasionally. Package, leaving ½-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select firm, ripe tomatoes with deep red color.

Raw – Wash and dip in boiling water for 30 seconds to loosen skins. Core and peel. Freeze whole or in pieces. Pack into containers, leaving l-inch headspace. Seal and freeze. Use only for cooking or seasoning as tomatoes will not be solid when thawed.

Juice – Wash, sort and trim firm, vine-ripened tomatoes. Cut in quarters or eighths. Simmer 5 to 10 minutes. Press through a sieve. If desired, season with 1 teaspoon salt to each quart of juice. Pour into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

Stewed – Remove stem ends, peel and quarter ripe tomatoes. Cover and cook until tender (10 to 20 minutes). Place pan containing tomatoes in cold water to cool. Pack into containers, leaving headspace. Seal and freeze.

</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select firm, sound green tomatoes. Wash, core, and slice 1/4-inch thick.

For Frying – Pack the slices into containers with freezer wrap between the slices. Leave 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item>Preparation – Select small to medium, firm turnips or parsnips that are tender and have a mild flavor. Wash, peel and cut into 1/2-inch cubes. Water blanch for 2 minutes. Cool promptly in cold water and drain. Pack into containers, leaving 1/2-inch headspace. Seal and freeze.</item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
    </string-array>


    <string-array name="vegetables_drying">
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
    </string-array>



    <string-array name="vegetables_canning">
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
        <item></item>
    </string-array>-->
</resources>